<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="CMIF">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Correspondence Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF)</title>
                <author key="dumont">Stefan Dumont</author>
                <author key="boerner">Ingo Börner</author>
                <author key="mueller-laackman">Jonas Müller-Laackman</author>
                <author key="leipold">Dominik Leipold</author>
                <author key="schneider">Gerlinde Schneider</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>
                <date when="2019-10-28"/>
                <idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163712891-8511250-2</idno>
                <idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/CMIF.html</idno>
                <idno type="zotero"
                    >https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/355VRRNR</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title type="main">Encoding Correspondence.</title>
                <title type="sub">A Manual for TEI-XML-based encoding of letters and postcards In
                    TEI-XML and DTABf</title>
                <editor>Stefan Dumont</editor>
                <editor>Susanne Haaf</editor>
                <editor>Sabine Seifert</editor>
                <idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163329488-8695229-7</idno>
                <idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/</idno>
                <biblScope unit="edition">v1</biblScope>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change n="1" when="2019-10-28" status="draft">Initial Version</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="c-1">
                <head>Objectives and principles</head>
                <p n="1">The Correspondence Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF) was developed for
                    editors of digital and printed scholarly editions to provide the most important
                    metadata about edited letters online and in a machine-readable form. This allows
                    for research, linking and analysis of correspondence across projects and
                    editions.</p>
                <p n="2">On the basis of CMIF, researchers are able to search for letters from or to
                    specific persons, places or within specific timespans across separate edition
                    projects, which makes new comprehensive searches possible. For example, it makes
                    it easier to search for letters by senders or recipients who do not have their
                    correspondence covered in an individual letter edition. It is also possible to
                    search for letters from a certain period, if necessary in connection with a
                    certain place of dispatch or reception. With the implementation of version 2 one
                    should be able to mark the entities mentioned in the letter (persons, places,
                    publications, events etc.). As a result, it will be possible for the first time
                    to use large collections of letters to answer systematic research questions such
                    as how the music business was organized in the 19th century or how a certain
                    event was received by contemporaries.</p>
                <p n="3">The CMIF - as a dedicated exchange format - covers exclusively metadata and
                    these only in a focused form. It does not include full text data, not least to
                    avoid legal problems. For the same reason, it can be distributed under a free
                    license. It cannot be seen as a replacement for a complete and detailed
                    teiHeader, which is specifically defined and used for individual editorial
                    projects. The CMIF file is provided as an addition to a scholarly edition and is
                    independent from the technologies and formats used for a given digital edition.
                    Therefore, for the provision of the CMIF data, it does not matter whether the
                    digital edition itself is based on XML, a relational database, or a graph
                    database. After all, CMIF can also be used to provide the metadata of edited
                    letters within a printed edition.</p>
                <p n="4">CMIF is intended exclusively for the exchange of relevant metadata beyond
                    project boundaries. It includes only those metadata that appear useful for
                    cross-project research, cross-linking and analysis. Put simply, the idea behind
                    CMIF is that information found in the index of letters, person, places etc. of
                    printed scholarly editions of correspondence can be provided digitally and in
                    machine-readable form.</p>
                <p n="5">The CMIF should enable fully automated exchange of data without needing
                    human intervention. To ensure this, the format must be restrictive and clearly
                    defined. Accordingly, when developing the format, the guiding principle was
                    "Keep it simple". By concentrating on essential metadata, the effort to provide
                    a CMIF file should also be kept as small as possible. In addition, an online
                    tool, the CMIF Creator, and detailed documentation are available.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2">
                <head>Background</head>
                <p n="6">CMIF is based on the guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) and
                    was developed within the <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/activities/sig/correspondence/">TEI Correspondence
                        Special Interest Group (SIG)</ref>. The initiative for the format was
                    started in 2014 in the workshop "Briefeditionen um 1800: Schnittstellen finden
                    und vernetzen", which was organized by Anne Baillot and Markus Schnöpf at the
                    Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities. Shortly before, a task
                    force of the TEI Correspondence SIG (namely Marcel Illetschko, Sabine Seifert
                    and Peter Stadler) had started to develop a new concept for encoding
                    correspondence metadata for the TEI guidelines - realized in the new element
                    &lt;correspDesc&gt; (Correspondence Description). It is supposed to encode the
                    most important communication-specific "header data" of a letter in TEI-XML in a
                    standardized way, in particular sender, recipient, place of writing and date.
                    The proposal for correspDesc was accepted by the TEI Council, revised and
                    incorporated into the TEI guidelines in April 2015. (Stadler, Illetschko, and
                    Seifert 2016; TEI Consortium 2019).</p>
                <p n="7">Already during the development of correspDesc, Peter Stadler outlined the
                    idea of developing a format for the exchange of correspondence metadata across
                    editions based on this new element. The element correspDesc should be used in a
                    significantly reduced and restrictive way to ensure an automated exchange of
                    data. A first draft of CMIF was developed following the workshop mentioned
                    above. Since then, CMIF has been developed and maintained within the framework
                    of the TEI Correspondence SIG. The schema definition using ODD and examples can
                    be found in the <ref target="https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF"
                        >GitHub repository of the SIG</ref>.</p>
                <p n="8">The TELOTA working group of the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and
                    Humanities developed the web service <ref target="https://correspsearch.net/"
                        >correspSearch</ref> in order to "fill CMIF with life", i.e. to demonstrate
                    the possible application scenarios. It aggregates CMIF files available online
                    and offers the metadata for convenient research or automatic retrieval via an
                    API. The web service currently aggregates (as of 1.10.2019) 110 CMIF files with
                    metadata to almost 54,000 edited letters in 178 publications. (Dumont 2016)</p>
                <p n="9">The Correspondence Metadata Interchange Format was awarded the <ref
                        target="https://tei-c.org/activities/rahtz-prize-for-tei-ingenuity/">"Rahtz
                        Prize for TEI Ingenuity 2018"</ref> together with the element correspDesc
                    and the web service correspSearch.</p>
                <p n="10">In the course of the workshop “Herausforderungen der Briefkodierung”
                    (“Challenges of letter encoding”) at the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences
                    and Humanities in October 2018, version 2 of the CMIF was developed based on the
                    initial considerations. </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-3">
                <head>General encoding principles</head>
                <p n="11">The formulated principle also has implications for a decision between two
                    variants for encoding. With regard to CMIF, two possible encoding variants exist
                    within the framework of the TEI guidelines:</p>
                <p n="12">On the one hand, it is possible to create one (albeit reduced) teiHeader
                    per letter and to use its capabilities (profileDesc, msDesc, keywords etc.) to
                    cover all necessary information. For an index of letters which includes the most
                    important metadata, several teiHeaders could then - to put it simply - be
                    combined in the element teiCorpus. Meta information on the letter index itself
                    could then be stored in the teiHeader of the teiCorpus element itself.</p>
                <p n="13">On the other hand, it is possible to create one single TEI document and
                    provide one correspDesc element per letter there. With this variant, meta
                    information on the CMIF file is directly indicated in the document's
                    teiHeader.</p>
                <p n="14">For the first version of CMIF, the second variant was chosen because it
                    posed hardly any problems as the element correspDesc (together with its child
                    elements) was completely sufficient for the desired metadata. In CMIF v1, only
                    the sender, the recipient, places of writing and receiving, date and the URL or
                    number of the letter are specified. This is what the TEI element correspDesc was
                    and is designed for. All other information - which is very manageable in terms
                    of numbers - can easily be placed in the teiHeader.</p>
                <p n="15">With the further development of CMIF to version 2, however, further
                    metadata - such as persons mentioned in a letter - for which the correspDesc
                    element is not intended per se can now be noted. In this context it was
                    discussed again whether one should not use the entire teiHeader per letter. At
                    first glance, this seems to be a clean solution, but one creates a large
                    "overhead" of TEI-XML encoding, which one would like to avoid for the reasons
                    already mentioned - "keep it simple". In addition, such a teiHeader would still
                    be greatly reduced compared to the teiHeader in the digital edition itself, but
                    would at the same time suggest completeness. In addition, with the second
                    encoding variant - i.e. the exclusive use of correspDesc - the CMIF can be
                    further developed to be downward compatible. All further considerations are now
                    based on the premise that the previously chosen encoding variant, which is
                    essentially based on the use of correspDesc, will be retained.</p>
                <p n="16">Here the fundamental question follows to what extent the CMIF should be
                    conform to the TEI guidelines. So far, no major problems occured with the use of
                    the TEI, which was essentially limited to the element correspDesc. But now - as
                    already discussed (Dumont 2015) - various further aspects have to be integrated
                    in correspDesc, which initially do not have their original location there. For
                    certain purposes, new attributes of their own would appear desirable, but they
                    would only be valid in CMIF and not generally in the TEI guidelines. Taking into
                    account the fact that the CMIF is rooted in the TEI community and the acceptance
                    based on it, the working group decided to focus on TEI conformity in the further
                    development of the format. According to the definitions of the TEI guidelines,
                    this includes, on the one hand, that the CMIF is validated against TEI All and,
                    on the other hand, that the TEI Abstract Model is implemented correctly. A
                    possible solution must take this into account.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-4">
                <head>Information to be included</head>
                <p n="17">Following these preliminary considerations, the question arises as to
                    which information should be included in the CMIF in addition to the information
                    already available in version 1. Hereof it is necessary to take the objectives of
                    the format postulated at the beginning into account: CMIF should enable both,
                    cross-project searches for letters and automated analysis of metadata, for
                    example for network research. The CMIF should not, as already mentioned, contain
                    the full range of metadata that is generated within a letter edition. The
                    relevance of the respective information for CMIF must be evaluated regarding its
                    necessity and usefulness in cross-project research or analysis. This is not
                    always a clear-cut decision. Of course, any information can increase the
                    research and analysis benefit of the data. However, previous experience has
                    shown that a cross-project metadata format is more accepted and used if only
                    absolutely necessary information has to be provided. On the other hand, the
                    effort for the project to provide its own metadata is the greater, the more
                    information has to be provided. An information-saturated, but complex metadata
                    format may seem ideal, but will find far less usage, which in turn greatly
                    diminishes its usefulness. Consequently, for pragmatic reasons, the format
                    should be kept manageable and simple.</p>
                <div xml:id="c-4-1">
                    <head>Information Contained in CMIF v1</head>
                    <p n="18">Until now, CMIF mainly contained the communication-specific metadata
                        of an edited letter: Sender, recipient, place of writing and receiving as
                        well as corresponding date information. In addition, number and/or the URL
                        of the letter can be noted. In addition, a bibliographic reference of the
                        scholarly edition is listed in the teiHeader.</p>
                    <p n="19">Apart from these letter- or edition-related details, the CMIF file
                        also contains metadata about the CMIF file itself (publisher, editor,
                        creation or modification date and URL of the file).</p>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="c-4-2">
                    <head>Information to be included in CMIF v2</head>
                    <div xml:id="c-4-2-1">
                        <head>Archives and Editions</head>
                        <p n="20">In CMIF v2, it should be possible to note information on the
                            identity of the letter in order to unambiguously identify or
                            disambiguate it. This can be an archival signature, or a unique ID of a
                            letter that is only printed. Such information is important in order to
                            research other editions of the same letter (or to recognize them as
                            such). The correspSearch web service already provides examples for this
                            from the currently aggregated CMIF files, but these are not yet
                            recognizable as such. The information is also important for the analysis
                            of metadata from CMIF files, to prevent letters from being redundantly
                            counted.</p>
                        <p n="21">Thus, references to the underlying archival document as well as to
                            other editions of the same letter should be able to be noted in CMIF v2.
                            This is relevant as <hi rendition="#i">automated</hi> differentiation or
                            linking of letters is not possible without high error rates since there
                            are too many cases in which different letters share the same basic data
                            (sender, recipient, location, date). The archival information would be
                            sufficient for identification, but there are also numerous cases in
                            which the original letter (or its draft or copy) is lost or in (unknown)
                            private possession. In these cases no archival information can be
                            provided and references must be made from one edition to the other.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="c-4-2-2">
                        <head>Uncertainty</head>
                        <p n="22">The labelling of uncertain information is an important part of
                            humanities scholarship - also when working with edited letters.
                            Considering the use of CMIF metadata for digital research methods, such
                            as historical network research, it should be possible for this
                            information to be noted in the CMIF for the concerned data.</p>
                        <p n="23">This includes the labelling of information that could not be
                            derived from the letter itself, but was taken from other sources or
                            originates the researcher’s conclusion. Primarily this concerns the
                            "header data" of a letter, such as sender and recipient, place of
                            writing and receipt as well as the corresponding date information. Here
                            it has always been common practice to place the respective data in the
                            letterhead in square brackets to indicate that this information was
                            "deduced" and could not be obtained from the original source itself.</p>
                        <p n="24">Deduced Information that does not originate from other sources but
                            from the investigations of the editor, can appear to have less or more
                            certainty. . For example, if the editor is not sure about a particular
                            information, it is not only marked with square brackets, but also with a
                            question mark. This makes it possible to offer the reader a suggestion
                            without specifying it is definitely correct. This practice of marking
                            uncertain assumptions is not only used for the header data of a letter,
                            but also in the body of the letter, if mentioned persons or places
                            cannot be identified unambiguously.</p>
                        <p n="25">In addition to these two practices to label uncertainty, there is
                            another one that concerns the letter as a whole: the copy text (textual
                            basis). In general, a letter should be edited on the original
                            manuscript. In case the original is lost, this is obviously not
                            possible. For this reason, the textual basis is always specified in
                            letter editions. Besides the original handwriting, this can be a copy by
                            the author (or their scribe), a copy by the recipient, a concept, a
                            draft or a later print. In any case, the existing textual basis
                            implicitly indicates the certainty by which it can be assumed that the
                            letter has reached its intended recipient and with what content.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="c-4-2-3">
                        <head>Entities mentioned</head>
                        <p n="26">The user of an edition of correspondence is inevitably very
                            interested in which letters certain persons, places, etc. are mentioned
                            This is why properly prepared indexes are an important component of
                            letter editions. The information contained in these registers is
                            therefore also of great interest to CMIF. Information about which
                            entities are mentioned in which letters would greatly facilitate
                            research across editions or even make possible in the first place. In
                            addition to “traditional” entity types found in the indexes of scholarly
                            editions, such as persons and places, other types of entities are
                            becoming increasingly of interest in recent years. These include
                            primarily publications, however, also events, objects and quotations are
                            feasible. The prerequisite for this would be the existence of authority
                            files that provide identifiers for these types of entities so that they
                            can be addressed across projects. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div xml:id="c-4-2-4">
                        <head>Type of publication</head>
                        <p n="27">So far, mainly edited letters have been discussed. However,
                            historical correspondence is provided on different editorial levels by
                            scholarship. These can range from simple archival repertories to regesta
                            to fully edited letters which include commentaries and facsimiles.
                            Information about the form in which a letter is ‘recorded’ is less
                            relevant for scholarly questions that can be answered using metadata,
                            however,it would support research in a meaningful way by enabling the
                            user to see whatto expect at the end - whether it is printed or
                            available online. This information would be particularly useful for
                            scholars who want to build a corpus. In addition, it can easily happen
                            that a letter is recorded differently in different projects. If data
                            sets from both projects are to be used in a research interface, it is
                            useful to be able to estimate the rough degree of recording there.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-5">
                <head>Encoding</head>
                <p n="28">Yet, it has to be answered how the desired information can be accommodated
                    considering the background of the basic encoding (see above) and in a
                    TEI-compliant way. If one wants to stick with the chosen approach and place all
                    information in the element correspDesc, only the attributes in correspDesc and
                    the child element correspDesc/note remain. The other two child elements
                    correspAction and correspContext are semantically and uniquely assigned to the
                    communication process so that they cannot be used as carriers for the additional
                    information, as described above.</p>
                <p n="29">In addition to the attributes, the element note, containing an
                    "annotation" according to the TEI definition, remains in place. Although the
                    information to be coded might not be covered by the proper meaning of
                    “annotation” , the broader field of meanings attributed to “annotation” in the
                    academic field is indeed much larger. Note can thus also be understood as an
                    annotation of the correspondence description (correspDesc), which includes the
                    information mentioned above.</p>
                <p n="30">Once note has been chosen as a container, the question remains to what
                    extent the listed information can be accommodated. Especially with regard to the
                    mentioned entities it seems obvious to use the relevant TEI elements, such as
                    persName. A coding would then look like this:</p>
                <figure>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <note type="mentioned">
                            <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/24602065">Johann Wolfgang von
                                Goethe</persName>
                            <placeName ref="http://www.geonames.org/2874225">Mainz</placeName>
                            <orgName ref="http://asa">Verlag XY</orgName>
                            <bibl sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/186077286">Die Leiden des jungen
                                Werthers</bibl>
                            <term ref="urn:lsid:ipni.org:names:164558-3:1.1">Kalanchoe
                                pinnata</term>
                            <date from="1793-04-14" to="1793-07-23">Belagerung von Mainz</date>
                        </note>
                    </egXML>
                    <figDesc>Example 1: Encoding mentioned entities with specific TEI
                        elements</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p n="31">With this encoding, however, the question quickly arises as to whether one
                    should go along in a more general way with rs (referencing string), which is
                    specified via a @type attribute. An example based on a person would look like
                    this:</p>

                <figure>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <rs type="person" ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/24602065"> Johann Wolfgang von
                            Goethe</rs>
                    </egXML>
                    <figDesc>Example 2: Encoding information with generalized &lt;rs&gt;</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p n="32">One advantage of this type of encoding would be a better flexibility when
                    using different entity types. These will become more differentiated in the
                    future and new ones will be added. For example, objects mentioned in letters
                    that have actually been handed down in museums and collections are
                    conceivable.</p>
                <p n="33">Based on this generic approach, the working group came up with the idea of
                    whether it would be possible to encode the references based on the triple
                    notation of the Semantic Web. The references are noted as simple statements
                    according to the pattern "subject - predicate - object". A natural linguistic
                    analogy of a triple would be: "Letter XY mentions Johann Wolfgang von Goethe".
                    For the purpose of machine-readable identification, corresponding URIs are used
                    for subject and object, which are best defined across projects, e.g. in the
                    common standards file. The predicate is also defined as a machine-readable URI.
                    Eventually, this vocabulary would be part of CMIF v2. To encode such triples
                    with TEI elements, the element relation is provided in the TEI guidelines. The
                    example could then look like this:</p>
                <figure>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <note type="mentioned">
                            <listRelation>
                                <relation active="http://example.org/letter-123"
                                    name="cmif:mentionsPerson"
                                    passive="http://viaf.org/viaf/24602065"> Johann Wolfgang von
                                    Goethe</relation>
                            </listRelation>
                        </note>
                    </egXML>
                    <figDesc>Example 3: Encoding information as triple with the help of
                        &lt;relation&gt;</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p n="34">The example 3 shows an accurate and convincing encoding in terms of
                    content. An advantage would also be that not only the mentioned entities, but
                    also other desired information could be coded, such as the URI of the archival
                    letter manuscript. </p>
                <p n="35">In the beginning, various attributes in the element correspDesc were
                    discussed, but it became clear that it would be difficult to find suitable ones
                    for archival information etc. To give an example, the @corresp attribute could
                    be used for the archive URI. The definition would allow this without further
                    ado, but it is also ambiguous for it does not make a clear statement about the
                    content. Beyond that it is desired to accommodate not only the URI of the
                    archival document, but also URIs of other editions of the letter. All URIs could
                    be noted in @corresp, but they could only be distinguished by their own names,
                    e.g. by calling them or registering them in a processing web service, such as
                    correspSearch. As a result, this would mean that this information would no
                    longer be contained in CMIF itself.</p>
                <p n="36">The proposed encoding with relations would therefore have the great
                    advantage of accommodating all desired information specifically. However, it
                    also has one disadvantage: this encoding is much more complicate than the other
                    encoding approaches. CMIF should be as simple as possible - both in terms of the
                    information to be included as well as the sort of encoding. Even so, could this
                    not be solved more easily? If one were to encode all the desired information as
                    in example 3, it would become apparent that the @active attribute always has the
                    same URI - namely that of the edited letter. But this is already clearly defined
                    by the element correspDesc as a whole and its attribute @ref. One idea would be
                    to use the TEI element ref instead of relation:</p>
                <figure>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ref type="cmif:mentionsPerson" target="http://viaf.org/viaf/24602065"
                            >Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</ref>
                    </egXML>
                    <figDesc>Example 4: Encoding information without the “subject” part.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p n="37">This way, one would stick to the approach with the exception that the
                    redundant "subject", i.e. the edited letter in the form of a URI, would be
                    omitted. The CMIF would remain clear and easy for people to understand.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-6">
                <head>Vocabulary and URIs</head>
                <p n="38">If the ref element is used generically for further information in CMIF v2,
                    it can be specified by the @type attribute to provide the differentiation
                    required for research and analysis. The attribute value consists of a URI from a
                    common vocabulary proposed in Table 1.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 1: Vocabulary for relationships (predicates)</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>URI<note xml:id="fn1" n="1"><p>Der Namensraum-Präfix “cmif” steht hier
                                    für einen noch zu definierenden Namensraum.</p></note></cell>
                        <cell>Description</cell>
                        <cell>@target (object)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:mentionsPerson</cell>
                        <cell>Person mentioned in the letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the person (VIAF, GND etc.)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:mentionsPlace</cell>
                        <cell>Place mentioned in the letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the place (GeoNames)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:mentionsOrg</cell>
                        <cell>Institution mentioned in the letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the institution</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:mentionsBibl</cell>
                        <cell>Publication mentioned in the letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the publication</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:mentionsObject</cell>
                        <cell>Object mentioned in the letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the object</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:mentionsEvent</cell>
                        <cell>Event mentioned in the letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the event</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:isEditionOf</cell>
                        <cell>The letter is an edition of an archival document</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the archival document (e.g. Kalliope-URI)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:seeAlso</cell>
                        <cell>Other data record (e.g. in another edition) for the same letter</cell>
                        <cell>URI of the (other) edited letter or record</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:hasTextBase</cell>
                        <cell>Edited letter hat as textbase</cell>
                        <cell>CMIF-URI (see table 2)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>cmif:isPublishedWith</cell>
                        <cell>Edited letter is published only as record or with regest,
                            transcription, commentary.</cell>
                        <cell>CMIF-URI (see table 3)</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p n="39">As in CMIF v1, URIs must be used for the targets (in ref/@target) in order
                    to ensure machine-readable identification of persons, locations, etc. This
                    assumes that there are suitable URIs for persons, places, etc. at all, which, if
                    possible, originate from an authority file. This is certainly problematic as
                    being discussed in the article on authority files. However, there are also
                    numerous cases in which entities do not have to be defined across projects. In
                    these cases, edition-internal URIs that identify or address corresponding
                    entities are also conceivable, even if little is known about the entity.
                    However, web services, which process CMIF files (e.g. correspSearch), have to
                    retrieve data (names, life dates etc.) in a standardized way via the URI. This
                    is currently neither customary nor sufficiently defined, so that further
                    development is necessary. Nevertheless, CMIF v2 should already provide this
                    option.</p>
                <p n="40">In addition to URIs from authority files, a specific vocabulary is
                    required that converts technical terms of scholarly editions of correspondence
                    into a machine-readable format.</p>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 2: Definition of Text Basis Types</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell rend="left">URI</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Definition</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:noTextBase</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Conjectured from mentions in other letters, diaries
                            etc.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:draft</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Draft</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:manuscript</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Manuscript</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:copy</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Copy (unspecified)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:copy-by-sender</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Transcript (initiated or written) by the sender</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:copy-by-addressee</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Transcript (initiated or written) by the addressee</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:copy-by-third</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Transcript (initiated or written) by a third person</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:print</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Letter only survived in printed form</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table rend="rules">
                    <head>Table 3: Type of information about the letter, provided in the scholarly
                        edition</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">URI</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Definition</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:record</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Record (only metadata)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:abstract</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Regest</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:transcription</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Transcription</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:comment</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Commentary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="left">cmif:facsimile</cell>
                        <cell rend="left">Digital facsimile</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p n="41">The encoding of a text base and the information, the edited letter is
                    published with, would then look like this:</p>
                <figure>
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ref type="cmif:hasTextBase" target="cmif:manuscript"/><ref
                            type="cmif:isPublishedWith" target="cmif:abstract"/>
                    </egXML>
                    <figDesc>Example 5: Text basis and type of available information about the
                        letter</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-7">
                <head>Conclusion </head>
                <p n="42">This proposal for version 2 of the Correspondence Metadata Interchange
                    Format is based on the principle that it should remain a lightweight,
                    restrictive format. The CMI format provides only the most relevant information
                    for research and analysis in order to maintain and further promote broad
                    acceptance and usage in the community. In this context, attention is also paid
                    to ensure fundamental conformance with the TEI guidelines.</p>
                <p n="43">As in CMIF v1, the correspDesc element remains at the core of the format
                    and includes all additional metadata. The proposed solution, based on
                    correspDesc/note/ref, uses Semantic Web concepts such as a simplified but
                    basically TEI-compliant triple notation, the use of URIs, and a controlled
                    vocabulary in the CMIF namespace. This will allow to capture other important
                    metadata - such as archival identifiers, uncertainties, and letter content - in
                    a highly operationalized form and to provide it in a lightweight interchange
                    format.</p>
                <p n="44">After evaluating and integrating the feedback from the scholarly
                    community, the proposal for CMIF v2 will be finalized in spring 2020 and
                    published with documentation, ODD files and examples in the GitHub repository of
                    the TEI Correspondence SIG.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl
                        sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/TZFE7DZW"
                        >Dumont, Stefan. 2015. ‘Perspectives of the Further Development of the
                        Correspondence Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF)’. <hi rendition="#i"
                            >Digiversity — Webmagazin Für Informationstechnologie in Den
                            Geisteswissenschaften (blog).</hi> 2015. <ref
                            target="https://digiversity.net/2015/perspectives-of-the-further-development-of-the-correspondence-metadata-interchange-format-cmif/"
                            >https://digiversity.net/2015/perspectives-of-the-further-development-of-the-correspondence-metadata-interchange-format-cmif/</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/9VYYBMPJ">
                        Dumont, Stefan. 2016. ‘CorrespSearch – Connecting Scholarly Editions of Letters’. In: 
                        <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi> 10. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1742">https://doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1742</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl
                        sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/KEWAE85C"
                        >Stadler, Peter, Marcel Illetschko, and Sabine Seifert. 2016. ‘Towards a
                        Model for Encoding Correspondence in the TEI: Developing and Implementing
                        &lt;correspDesc&gt;. In: <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Text Encoding
                            Initiative</hi> 9. <ref
                            target="https://dx.doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1742"
                            >https://dx.doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1742</ref>.</bibl>
                    <bibl
                        sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/TMLGNZ5L"
                        >TEI Consortium, ed. 2019. ‘Correspondence Description’. In <hi
                            rendition="#i">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                            Interchange</hi>. Version 3.6.0, 63–65. <ref
                            target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD"
                            >https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD</ref>.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
