<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="introduction">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Introduction</title>
				<author key="dumont">Stefan Dumont</author>
				<author key="haaf">Susanne Haaf</author>
				<author key="seifert">Sabine Seifert</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>
				<date when="2019-12-15"/>
				<idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163942154-1974512-7</idno>
				<idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/introduction.html</idno>
				<idno type="zotero"
					>https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/CGIQCIKJ</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title type="main">Encoding Correspondence.</title>
				<title type="sub">A Manual for encoding letters and postcards in TEI-XML and
					DTABf</title>
				<editor>Stefan Dumont</editor>
				<editor>Susanne Haaf</editor>
				<editor>Sabine Seifert</editor>
				<idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163329488-8695229-7</idno>
				<idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/</idno>
				<biblScope unit="edition">v1</biblScope>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Born digital.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<listChange>
				<change n="1" when="2019-10-10" status="draft">Initial Version</change>
			</listChange>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="c-1">
				<p n="1">Whether letters, postcards, telegrams, e-mails, sms, or
					chats—correspondence between different agents is and for a very long time has
					been a crucial part of everyday’s life with just as much impact on private as on
					work and public lives. Naturally, already before the permeation of technology in
					our society, written correspondence captured vast amounts of people’s time. And
					today, the direct and simple ways of digital communication are used even more
					extensively.</p>
				<p n="2">As for historical correspondence, we gain insight in this extremely
					productive area by letters passed on to us which were written by scholars,
					politicians, artists, celebrities, or private persons. This way, we do not only
					learn about the impact of correspondence by the sheer amount of documents
					available in archives. These documents are also witnesses of peoples’ broad
					networks and of the topics which concerned them. They deliver insight in private
					views on public affairs as well as in everyday’s problems of historical persons
					of interest.</p>
				<p n="3">Thus, and not surprisingly, historical documents of communication quite
					frequently have become the subject of humanities’ research and are prepared in
					scholarly editions in order to enable and facilitate further research. Since
					nowadays editions are usually digital-born and, most of the time, also remain
					digital, this area has increasingly been attracting the attention of the <ref
						target="https://tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> community.
					Letters, for instance, may appear quite homogeneously structured at first sight
					but—as transient documents—tend to exhibit various peculiarities and exceptions
					from customary practice. And more generally, the available text types for
					communication changed over time, the text types themselves changed in their
					specific style and structuring as did the contexts in which these text types
					were typically used.</p>
				<p n="4">As conveners of the <ref
						target="https://tei-c.org/Activities/SIG/Correspondence/">TEI Correspondence
						Special Interest Group (SIG)</ref><note n="1" xml:id="fn1">See also <ref
							target="https://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/SIG:Correspondence">the Wiki
							page of the TEI Correspondence SIG</ref>.</note> and representative for
					the <ref target="http://deutschestextarchiv.de/doku/basisformat/">Deutsches
						Textarchiv (DTA) Base Format</ref> (Haaf/Geyken/Wiegand 2014/15), we were
					repeatedly asked about the TEI encoding of correspondence-specific phenomena. In
					2015, the TEI Correspondence SIG had already addressed some of the problems with
					TEI encoding correspondence by introducing a new correspondence model to the TEI
					Guidelines with <gi>correspDesc</gi> and its several child elements
					(Stadler/Illetschko/Seifert 2016).<note n="2" xml:id="fn2">Also cf. the TEI
						Guidelines, <ref
							target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD"
							>chapter 2.4.6: Correspondence Description</ref>.</note> The DTA Base
					Format, which had started off as a format for printed texts, was opened to
					manuscript texts and enriched with markup for manuscript-specific phenomena in
					2016 so that, among other things, it enables the integration of handwritten or
					typed (in addition to printed) letters in the DTA text corpus (Haaf/Thomas
					2017).</p>
				<p n="5">Apart from mere correspondence annotation, there also was and is a growing
					demand to effectively link correspondence editions and projects in order to
					reveal correspondence networks of the ‘Republic of Letters’ and beyond. This
					desideratum led to the creation of the <ref
						target="https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF">Correspondence
						Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF)</ref>—a constrained subset of the full
					TEI standard of the <gi>correspDesc</gi> element—and to the development of the
					web service <ref target="https://correspsearch.net/">correspSearch</ref> (Dumont
					2016) with CMIF as exchange format. In 2018, the Rahtz Prize for TEI Ingenuity
					was granted to the developers of the <gi>correspDesc</gi> encoding model, the
					CMIF and correspSearch.<note n="3" xml:id="fn3">Namely to Stefan Dumont, Sascha
						Grabsch, Marcel Illetschko, Jonas Müller-Laackman, Sabine Seifert, and Peter
						Stadler, <ref
							target="https://tei-c.org/activities/rahtz-prize-for-tei-ingenuity/."
							>https://tei-c.org/activities/rahtz-prize-for-tei-ingenuity/</ref>.</note></p>
				<p n="6">However, there are still open questions on how to deal with several
					structural and textual occurrences, and work on creating an exhaustive
					environment for the TEI encoding of letters is not yet finished. As a next step,
					we decided to hold a workshop on these “Challenges of Letter Encoding” which
					would provide a forum for further discussions on problematic cases of
					correspondence encoding in TEI. The aim was to develop solutions and best
					practices within the range of possibilities already offered by the TEI, and, if
					necessary, to produce suggestions of potential extensions to the TEI.</p>
				<p n="7">The workshop was funded by CLARIN-D and was held at the Berlin-Brandenburg
					Academy of Sciences and Humanities (BBAW) in Berlin (Germany) in October 2018.
					We invited early-career researchers who deal with TEI encoding and/or especially
					correspondence encoding in the course of their daily work, as well as one member
					of the TEI Council for advice on proposals for TEI extensions. Some 20
					participants from 15 institutions in Germany, Austria and Switzerland got
					together for the workshop.</p>
				<p n="8">Before the event, we gathered examples of insecurities or problems with
					applying TEI to correspondence texts from the participants, which were then
					dealt with in the course of the workshop. Based on this material, we formed five
					groups of (roughly) related encoding issues, and 4-5 participants per group were
					asked to discuss the given issues: <list>
						<item>Group I: Text structures I (dealing with openers, closers,
							postscripts)</item>
						<item>Group II: Text structures II (dealing with pre-printed parts like
							letterheads, addresses, stamps, seals, postcards etc.)</item>
						<item>Group III: Metadata I (dealing with attachments, roles like author,
							scribe, and sender, actions like commenting etc.)</item>
						<item>Group IV: Metadata II (dealing with unclear information)</item>
						<item>Group V: CMIF and Metadata (dealing with the extension of CMIF,
							authority files and modelling correspondence in RDF)</item>
					</list></p>
				<p n="9">The meeting was designed as a hands-on workshop, enabling the groups of
					participants to discuss the issues and material presented to them and to develop
					solutions. These sessions of group work were alternating with plenary sessions
					for discussions of problems and solutions across groups. All issues discussed
					concerned aspects of letter or postcard encoding: from correspondence-specific
					text structures to correspondence metadata. Subsequent to the workshop, the
					problems, discussions, and recommendations were summarized as handbook articles
					by the workshop participants. The articles underwent an internal review phase,
					and are now published in successive stages on this website for the community to
					comment and review. The articles now online and the ones coming soon are all in
					version 1 and remain as such stable. The public review phase lasts until 30
					April 2020. Then, all articles will be revised and adapted, and made available
					in their final version here, as a version 2 of the handbook. </p>
				<p n="10">This resulting handbook “Encoding Correspondence. A manual for encoding
					letters and postcards in TEI-XML and DTABf” is meant as a guide for annotators
					on characteristic and recurring problems of letter encoding in TEI, offering
					solutions and recommendations based on the TEI Guidelines, as well as possible
					extensions to the TEI. Next to these articles discussing the respective issues
					in a more or less longer manner, we plan, as a long-term objective, to provide a
					best practice guide of how to encode correspondence material for a quick and
					short overview.</p>
				<p n="11">The literature used as well as the bibliographic information for each
					article itself are additionally stored in the <ref
						target="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/"
						>Zotero group "Encoding Correspondence"</ref> and embedded as <ref
						target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COinS">"COinS"</ref> in the HTML
					version of this manual. Therefore, one can add the bibliographic data to a
					literature management software with the appropriate browser extension (e.g. with
					Zotero or the Citavi Picker).</p>
				<p n="12">As this is a community effort, we kindly invite you to comment on or
					review the articles, ask questions, give feedback, add examples of
					correspondence or encoding, or whatever you find helpful for making this a
					valuable resource for encoders of correspondence. This can be done with the
					easy-to-use annotating tool <ref target="https://web.hypothes.is/"
						>Hypothes.is</ref> or by using the e-mail button at the side of each
					article.</p>
				<p n="13">The complete handbook with all articles (but except the comments via
					Hypothes.is) is availabe for download at GitHub: <ref
						target="https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/encoding-correspondence"
						>https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/encoding-correspondence</ref>.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="bibliography">
				<head>Bibliography</head>
				<listBibl>
					<bibl
						sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/9VYYBMPJ"
						>Dumont, Stefan. 2016. ‟correspSearch – Connecting Scholarly Editions of
						Letters.ˮ <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi>
						10. <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1742"
							>http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1742</ref>.</bibl>
					<bibl
						sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/ZJYUY9AL"
						>Haaf, Susanne, Alexander Geyken, and Frank Wiegand. 2014/15. ‟The DTA 'Base
						Format': A TEI Subset for the Compilation of a Large Reference Corpus of
						Printed Text from Multiple Sources.ˮ <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Text
							Encoding Initiative</hi> 8. <ref
							target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1114"
							>http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1114</ref>.</bibl>
					<bibl
						sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/3KQ6GAUR"
						>Haaf, Susanne and Christian Thomas. 2017. ‟Enabling the Encoding of
						Manuscripts within the DTABf: Extension and Modularization of the Format.ˮ
							<hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Text Encoding Initiative</hi> 10
						(2016–2019). <ref target="http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1650"
							>http://journals.openedition.org/jtei/1650</ref>.</bibl>
					<bibl
						sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/KEWAE85C"
						>Stadler, Peter, Marcel Illetschko, and Sabine Seifert. 2016. ‟Towards a
						Model for Encoding Correspondence in the TEI: Developing and Implementing
						&lt;correspDesc&gt;.ˮ <hi rendition="#i">Journal of the Text Encoding
							Initiative</hi> 9. <ref target="https://dx.doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1742"
							>https://dx.doi.org/10.4000/jtei.1742</ref>.</bibl>
					<bibl
						sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/TMLGNZ5L"
						>TEI Consortium, ed. 2019. ‟Correspondence Description.ˮ In <hi
							rendition="#i">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
							Interchange</hi>. Version 3.6.0, 63–65. <ref
							target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD"
							>https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD</ref>.</bibl>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
