<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pre-printed-parts">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pre-printed parts: Letterheads and forms</title>
            <author key="seifert">Sabine Seifert</author>
            <author key="schenk">Nicolas Schenk</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>
            <date when="2019-12-14"/>
            <idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163911057-9256446-7</idno>
            <idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/pre-printed-parts.html</idno>
            <idno type="zotero">https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/HRW8FC25</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title type="main">Encoding Correspondence.</title>
            <title type="sub">A manual for encoding letters and postcards in TEI-XML and
               DTABf</title>
            <editor>Stefan Dumont</editor>
            <editor>Susanne Haaf</editor>
            <editor>Sabine Seifert</editor>
            <idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163329488-8695229-7</idno>
            <idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/</idno>
            <biblScope unit="edition">v1</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change n="1" when="2019-12-14" status="draft">Initial Version</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="c-1">
            <head xml:id="introduction">Introduction</head>
            <p n="1">Correspondence materials often contain pre-printed parts for which there are no
               sufficient or satisfying encoding recommendations in the TEI Guidelines. These
               pre-printed parts can be divided into two categories. First, there is the typical
               case of letterheads, usually with name and address of the sender, maybe including a
               company emblem, family crest or other kind of symbol. And second, there are
               pre-printed parts similar to printed forms, for example address fields with labels
               and dotted lines to fill in on postcards, envelopes, or letters.</p>
            <p n="2">Both cases represent pre-printed parts but constitute semantically different
               phenomena. It is, therefore, necessary to make a basic distinction between these two
               cases regarding their encoding in TEI.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="c-2">
            <head xml:id="letterheads">Case 1: Letterheads</head>
            <div xml:id="c-2-1">
               <head xml:id="issue1-1">Issue 1: Using <gi>fw</gi></head>
               <p n="3"> One suggested possibility to encode letterheads is using the element
                     <gi>fw</gi>.<note n="1" xml:id="fn1">For this and the discussion of encoding
                     letterheads see the TEI-L Mailinglist: <ref target="http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/correspondence-encoding-problems-letter-headings-td4029408.html">http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/correspondence-encoding-problems-letter-headings-td4029408.html</ref>.
                  </note> The TEI Guidelines define <gi>fw</gi> as follows:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>fw</gi> (forme work) contains a running head (e.g. a header, footer),
                     catchword, or similar material appearing on the current page.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-fw.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-fw.html</ref>
               </cit>
               <p n="4">Next to running heads and footers, i.e. titles of chapters in printed books,
                  this element is also intended for page numbers, catchwords, and "other material
                  repeated from page to page, which falls outside the stream of the text".<note n="2" xml:id="fn2">
                     <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html#PHSK">Chapter 11.6 "Headers, Footers, and Similar Matter"</ref> of the TEI
                     Guidelines.</note> The question is whether letterheads fall in these categories
                  or whether this is an overexpansion of the definition and therefore a misuse of
                     <gi>fw</gi>.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 1: Letter with letterhead (source: Théophile Peyron to Vincent van
                     Gogh, 1 July 1890. Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b1064 V/1962, <ref target="http://vangoghletters.org/vg/letters/let895/letter.html">http://vangoghletters.org/vg/letters/let895/letter.html</ref>).</head>
                  <graphic url="../images/pre-printed-parts/example1.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p n="5">A possible encoding using <gi>fw</gi> might look like this (example 1):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <fw type="letterhead" place="top-left">Maison de
                        Santé<lb/>de<lb/>Saint-Rémy<lb/>de Provence<lb/>Bouches-du-Rhône</fw>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="6">The element <gi>fw</gi> is quite flexible and allows names, places, and
                  addresses to be marked up with <gi>address</gi>, <gi>name</gi>, <gi>placeName</gi>
                  etc. to further specify the content of the letterhead. <gi>figure</gi> can also be
                  included to capture images that are part of the letterhead (for this, see <ref target="#c-2-4">Case 1: Letterheads, issue 4</ref>). There is, however, the
                  question whether <gi>fw</gi> being an inline element is problematic or not as
                  letterheads in their layout are usually set apart from the rest of the text.</p>
               <p n="7">The encoding of a combined letterhead and—as one might call it—letterfooter
                  might look like this:<note n="3" xml:id="fn3">Encoding example (slightly changed)
                     taken from <ref target="http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/correspondence-encoding-problems-letter-headings-td4029408.html">http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/correspondence-encoding-problems-letter-headings-td4029408.html</ref>.</note>
               </p>
               
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div>
                        <pb n="1"/>
                        <fw type="letterhead">[...]</fw>
                        <opener>[...]</opener>
                        <p>[...]</p>
                        <fw type="letterfooter">[...]</fw>
                        <pb n="2"/>
                        <fw type="letterhead">[...]</fw>
                        <p>[...]</p>
                        <closer>[...]</closer>
                        <fw type="letterfooter">[...]</fw>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="8">Here, you can see this structure in an example encoding of a letter from
                  Johnny Cash to Saul Holiff, written in 1961:<note n="4" xml:id="fn4">Letter from
                     Johnny Cash to Saul Holiff, 6 June 1961: <ref target="https://exhibits.library.uvic.ca/spotlight/holiff/catalog/11-12904">https://exhibits.library.uvic.ca/spotlight/holiff/catalog/11-12904</ref>.
                     Another example for writing paper with letterhead and footer is the letter from
                     Eugene Belmont to Harry Ault, 2 July 1932: <ref target="https://digitalcollections.lib.washington.edu/digital/collection/pioneerlife/id/8634/">https://digitalcollections.lib.washington.edu/digital/collection/pioneerlife/id/8634/</ref>.</note></p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div>
                        <pb n="1"/>
                        <fw type="letterhead">A Few Very Rural, Badly Phrased But Well Meant Words
                           From<lb/>Johnny Cash</fw>
                        <opener>
                           <address>
                              <addrLine>4259 Hayvenhurst Ave</addrLine>
                              <addrLine>[...]</addrLine>
                           </address>
                           <salute>Dear Mr. Volatile,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Thanks very much for the pictures. [...]</p>
                        <fw type="letterfooter">Singer - Song Writer - Guitar Picker - Cotton
                           Picker</fw>
                        <pb n="2"/>
                        <fw type="letterhead">A Few Very Rural, Badly Phrased But Well Meant Words
                           From<lb/>Johnny Cash</fw>
                        <p>Concerning the cities proposed, [...]</p>
                        <closer>
                           <salute>Gotta go. Thanks again for the pictures. If you need any help
                              from this end, let me know.</salute>
                           <signed>J.R.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <fw type="letterfooter">Singer - Song Writer - Guitar Picker - Cotton
                           Picker</fw>
                        <pb n="3"/>
                        <fw type="letterhead">A Few Very Rural, Badly Phrased But Well Meant Words
                           From<lb/>Johnny Cash</fw>
                        <postscript>
                           <label>P.S.</label>
                           <p>Gordon went to Las Vegas over the weekend [...]</p>
                           <signed>J.R.</signed>
                        </postscript>
                        <fw type="letterfooter">Singer - Song Writer - Guitar Picker - Cotton
                           Picker</fw>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="9">While this encoding might be suitable for letterheads with names and
                  addresses, it seems not so fitting for pre-printed parts with gaps to be filled in
                  by the letter writer (for this, see <ref target="#c-3-2">Case 2: Pre-printed parts
                     like forms, issue 2</ref>).</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-2">
               <head xml:id="issue1-2">Issue 2: Using <gi>opener</gi> or <gi>head</gi></head>
               <p n="10">As letterheads are often positioned at the top or bottom of the paper, one
                  might think about using the elements <gi>opener</gi> or <gi>closer</gi> with a
                  type attribute that contains, for example, the value letterhead. While
                     <gi>opener</gi> with rend="letterhead" and <gi>closer</gi> with
                  rend="letterhead" before and after the actual <gi>opener</gi> and <gi>closer</gi>
                  might seem like viable solutions, they represent in fact a tag abuse as
                  letterheads are not covered by the definitions of these two elements.<note n="5" xml:id="fn5"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-opener.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-opener.html</ref>, and
                        <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-closer.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-closer.html</ref>.
                  </note></p>
               <p n="11">The same is true for the element <gi>head</gi><note n="6" xml:id="fn6"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-head.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-head.html</ref>.</note>
                  which, moreover, cannot capture letterheads at other places than the top of the
                  page. As printed letterheads need not necessarily be on the top of the letter
                  paper above the letter text, they can be positioned at the bottom, on the left or
                  right side, or centered. Therefore, the encoding of letterheads should be
                  independent of their position on the paper but solely based on their content.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-3">
               <head xml:id="issue1-3">Issue 3: Using <gi>div</gi>, <gi>seg</gi> or
                  <gi>ab</gi></head>
               <p n="12">There is also the possibility of encoding printed letterheads not with an
                  'individual' element but in a more general way as divisions, segments, or even as
                  anonymous blocks. The definitions of these elements <gi>div</gi>, <gi>seg</gi>,
                  and <gi>ab</gi> do not exactly apply to letterheads but could be considered
                  semantically close:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>div</gi> (text division) contains a subdivision of the front, body, or
                     back of a text.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-div.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-div.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>seg</gi> (arbitrary segment) represents any segmentation of text below
                     the 'chunk' level.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-seg.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-seg.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>ab</gi> (anonymous block) contains any arbitrary component-level unit
                     of text, acting as an anonymous container for phrase or inter level elements
                     analogous to, but without the semantic baggage of, a paragraph.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-ab.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-ab.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <p n="13">The <gi>div</gi> element can be further specified with a type attribute
                  containing "letterhead", "letterfooter", and "pre-printed-form" as possible
                  values, or, in a similar manner, a type attribute containing a general value
                  "pre-printed" accompanied by additional subtypes "letterhead", "letterfooter", or
                  "pre-printed-form". Next to a type attribute, a rend attribute with a value like
                  "pre-printed" also seems possible. However, these encodings pose problems as, for
                  example, <gi>div</gi> and <gi>ab</gi> are not allowed before <gi>opener</gi> or
                  after <gi>closer</gi>. Putting them after <gi>opener</gi> and before
                     <gi>closer</gi>, respectively, is in many cases not a faithful encoding of the
                  source. <gi>seg</gi> is an inline element and cannot be used outside <gi>div</gi>
                  that again is not allowed before <gi>opener</gi> or after <gi>closer</gi>. It
                  should, however, not be put inside <gi>opener</gi> or <gi>closer</gi>,
                  respectively, as it cannot be considered a part of these.</p>
               <p n="14">Another problem arises when dealing with letters several pages long and
                  with a recurring (or even changing) letterhead on each page. An encoding like
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="letter">
                        <div type="letterhead"/>
                        <div type="letterbody"/>
                     </div>
                  </egXML> would result in several <gi>div</gi> with type="letterbody", one for each
                  single page, interrupted by the recurring <gi>div</gi> with type="letterhead".
                  This seems neither practical nor appropriate.</p>
               <p n="15">Finally, all three elements <gi>div</gi>, <gi>seg</gi>, and <gi>ab</gi>
                  seem rather unspecific regarding the encoding of letterheads, and are probably too
                  general.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-4">
               <head xml:id="issue1-4">Issue 4: Using <gi>figure</gi></head>
               <p n="16">As letterheads very often include an image or graphical element, and are
                  "typically the result of a lay-out process in the design of the letter paper"<note n="7" xml:id="fn7"><ref target="http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/correspondence-encoding-problems-letter-headings-td4029408.html">http://tei-l.970651.n3.nabble.com/correspondence-encoding-problems-letter-headings-td4029408.html</ref>.</note>,
                  an encoding using <gi>figure</gi> with type="letterhead" comes to mind. The
                  element <gi>figure</gi> can occur in many different places and can be used in
                  varying depth. On the one hand, it can be used as an empty element for merely
                  signalling the presence of a letterhead. On the other hand, it can contain a
                  description (in <gi>figDesc</gi>), a digital image (in <gi>graphic</gi>), and/or a
                  transcription of its text.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 2: Letter with image in letterhead (source: Theodor Fontane to
                     Emilie Fontane, 14 August 1856. Potsdam, Theodor-Fontane-Archiv, shelf number
                     TFA V III,4 (Andr), <ref target="https://www.fontanearchiv.de/handschriften/12000250/">https://www.fontanearchiv.de/handschriften/12000250/</ref>. </head>
                  <graphic url="../images/pre-printed-parts/example2.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p n="17">A possible encoding using <gi>figure</gi> might look like this (example
                  2):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div type="letter">
                        <figure type="letterhead">
                           <figDesc>The figure shows a drawing of Shakespeare's birthplace in
                              Stratford-upon-Avon, England.</figDesc>
                           <graphic url="fig1.jpg"/>
                           <head>Shakspeare's birth place</head>
                           <p>Published by E. Adams</p>
                        </figure>
                        <opener>Meine liebe Frau. [...]</opener>
                        <p>[...]</p>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="18">Its use is very flexible but the definition suggests that using
                     <gi>figure</gi> like that is rather a tag abuse:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>figure</gi> groups elements representing or containing graphic
                     information such as an illustration, formula, or figure.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-figure.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-figure.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <p n="19">Any text contained within <gi>figure</gi> is being understood as
                  "commentary on the figure in the source"<note n="8" xml:id="fn8"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/FT.html#FTGRA">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/FT.html#FTGRA</ref>.</note>
                  which is not the case in each and every letterhead. Sometimes, there may be text
                  accompanying and commenting the image, as in example 2. However, it usually is the
                  case that text and image are on a parallel level to each other, or the image is an
                  illustration of the text, not the text a commentary on the image. The image might
                  also be just an additional, beautifying feature, like an ornamental decoration as
                  in the letterhead in example 1. Therefore, the text of letterheads should not be
                  subordinate to its image and be transcribed within <gi>figure</gi>. If there is no
                  image at all, as in example 3, an encoding of the letterhead—although perhaps
                  containing a graphical layout—with <gi>figure</gi> seems counterintuitive.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 3: Letter with letterhead (source: Vincent van Gogh to Theo van
                     Gogh, 24 March 1873. Amsterdam, Van Gogh Museum, inv. no. b6 V/1962, <ref target="http://vangoghletters.org/vg/letters/let006/letter.html">http://vangoghletters.org/vg/letters/let006/letter.html</ref>).</head>
                  <graphic url="../images/pre-printed-parts/example3.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p n="20"><gi>figure</gi> is also not suitable for pre-printed parts with, for
                  example, a place and a dotted line to fill in the date (see <ref target="#c-3-3">Case 2: Pre-printed parts like forms, issue 3</ref>).</p>
               <p n="21">Even though <gi>figure</gi> is not suitable for complete letterheads, it
                  can be used for just the image. It can be part of <gi>fw</gi> and a possible
                  encoding of example 2 might look like this:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="letter">
                        <fw type="letterhead">
                           <figure>
                              <figDesc>The figure shows a drawing of Shakespeare's birthplace in
                                 Stratford-upon-Avon, England.</figDesc>
                              <graphic url="fig1.jpg"/>
                              <head>Shakspeare's birth place</head>
                              <p>Published by E. Adams</p>
                           </figure>
                        </fw>
                        <opener>Meine liebe Frau. [...]</opener>
                        <p>[...]</p>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-5">
               <head xml:id="issue1-5">Issue 5: Using <gi>layoutDesc</gi></head>
               <p n="22">A basic decision is whether the information of the existence of a
                  letterhead and its content are needed in the transcription or whether abstracting
                  these information and putting them in the meta data is sufficient. The latter may
                  be more convenient for projects that consider the exact transcription of
                  letterheads not semantically important, and for projects with large corpuses of
                  letters with numerous letterheads.</p>
               <p n="23">For including these information in the meta data, <gi>layoutDesc</gi> as
                  part of <gi>objectDesc</gi> is a suitable place:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>layoutDesc</gi> (layout description) collects the set of layout
                     descriptions applicable to a manuscript or other object.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-layoutDesc.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-layoutDesc.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <p n="24">A simple encoding example might look like this:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><objectDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout>A letterhead is printed at the top of the paper with the company's
                           name and address.</layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p n="25">Additionally, it might be useful to link the information encoded in
                     <gi>layoutDesc</gi> with the transcription of the letterhead in the
                     <gi>body</gi>. For the letter to Vincent van Gogh in example 1, we recommend an
                  encoding like this in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> as well as in <gi>body</gi>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><objectDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <layout xml:id="lh">A letterhead is printed in the top left corner of the
                              paper with the hotel's name and address in which the sender was
                              staying.</layout>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <!-- [...] -->
                     <div>
                        <fw type="letterhead" place="top-left" corresp="#lh">Maison de
                           Santé<lb/>de<lb/>Saint-Rémy<lb/>de Provence<lb/>Bouches-du-Rhône</fw>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="26">For the linking of the letterhead in the <gi>body</gi> part with the
                  header, one cannot use @ref within <gi>fw</gi>, as this is not allowed according
                  to the TEI Guidelines. It is also not allowed to use the <gi>ref</gi> element
                  inside <gi>div</gi>. Therefore, the <gi>ref</gi> element needs to be put inside
                     <gi>fw</gi> containing the transcription of the letterhead. The target
                  attribute then points to the <gi>layout</gi> element in the header:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div>
                        <fw type="letterhead" place="top-left">
                           <ref target="#lh">Maison de Santé<lb/>de<lb/>Saint-Rémy<lb/>de
                              Provence<lb/>Bouches-du-Rhône</ref>
                        </fw>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-6">
               <head xml:id="issue1-6">Using <gi>supportDesc</gi></head>
               <p n="27">If one understands the information on pre-printed letterheads on the paper
                  as information about the supporting material on which the letter is written or
                  typed, the element <gi>supportDesc</gi> (as part of <gi>objectDesc</gi>) might
                  first look like a suitable place:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>supportDesc</gi> (support description) groups elements describing the
                     physical support for the written part of a manuscript or other object.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-supportDesc.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-supportDesc.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <p n="28">This is a handling of letterheads similar to, for example, watermarks.
                  However, this rather relates to the actual material and its physical aspects<note n="9" xml:id="fn9">Cf. the definition of <gi>support</gi>: "<gi>support</gi>
                     contains a description of the materials etc. which make up the physical support
                     for the written part of a manuscript or other object" <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-support.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-support.html</ref>.</note>
                  than to information printed on these materials. Therefore, <gi>supportDesc</gi>
                  cannot be recommended for encoding letterheads.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="c-3">
            <head xml:id="forms">Case 2: Pre-printed parts like forms</head>
            <p n="29">Pre-printed parts are a recurring phenomenon in correspondence materials, and
               can be found on telegrams and postcards. A proper markup in order to distinguish
               pre-printed text from handwritten text may be helpful when it comes to research
               questions focusing, for example, on the relation of pre-printed and handwritten text
               in letters and how the first may influence the (genesis of) the latter.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Example 4: field postcard (source: Franz Marc to Herwarth Walden, 17 April
                  1915, in: DER STURM. Digitale Quellenedition zur Geschichte der internationalen
                  Avantgarde, <ref target="https://sturm-​edition.de/id/Q.01.19150417.FMA.01">https://sturm-​edition.de/id/Q.01.19150417.FMA.01</ref>).</head>
               <graphic url="../images/pre-printed-parts/example4.png"/>
            </figure>
            <div xml:id="c-3-1">
               <head xml:id="issue2-1">Issue 1: Using <gi>ab</gi></head>
               <p n="30">On the textual level, one solution might be the use of the block element
                     <gi>ab</gi><note n="10" xml:id="fn10"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-ab.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-ab.html</ref>.</note>
                  in order to distinguish between pre-printed and non-pre-printed parts. <gi>ab</gi>
                  then might use the attribute–value pair type="pre-printed" for pre-printed parts,
                  type="typed" for text which is produced by a typewriter and type="handwritten" for
                  handwritten text to make the distinction.</p>
               <p n="31">An encoding of the field postcard in example 4 might look as follows
                  (simplified, deletions by sender not encoded):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ab type="pre-printed">Absender:</ab>
                     <ab type="handwritten">Vizewachtm. Marc</ab>
                     <ab type="handwritten">Galde<lb/>Fuchs</ab>
                     <ab type="pre-printed">Armeekorps<lb/>Division</ab>
                     <ab type="handwritten"><lb/><lb/>Ersatz</ab>
                     <ab type="pre-printed">Regiment No<lb/>Bataillon<lb/>Abteilung</ab>
                     <ab type="pre-printed">Kompagnie<lb/>Batterie<lb/>Eskadron<lb/>Kolonne</ab>
                     <ab type="pre-printed">Besondere Formationen: (Flieger, Funker usw.)</ab>
                     <ab type="handwritten">Schilling der 1. bayr. Feld-​Art. Rgt. Leichte-​Mun.
                        Kol.</ab>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="32">When encoded like this, we cannot see which handwritten addition belongs to
                  which pre-printed part. One could solve this problem by an encoding like the
                  following (with a different segmentation of the text used in order to group the
                  associated parts):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Absender:</ab>
                        <ab type="handwritten">Vizewachtm. Marc</ab>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <ab type="handwritten">Galde</ab>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Armeekorps</ab>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <ab type="handwritten">Fuchs</ab>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Division</ab>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Regiment No</ab>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <ab type="handwritten">Ersatz</ab>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Bataillon<lb/>Abteilung</ab>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Kompagnie<lb/>Batterie<lb/>Eskadron<lb/>Kolonne</ab>
                     </div>
                     <div>
                        <ab type="pre-printed">Besondere Formationen: (Flieger, Funker usw.)</ab>
                        <ab type="handwritten">Schilling der 1. bayr. Feld-​Art. Rgt. Leichte-​Mun.
                           Kol.</ab>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="33">The attribute-value pairs mentioned above do not follow any conventions in
                  TEI; the type attribute can be used in order to annotate completely different
                  phenomena. Thus, this solution seems unspecific with regard to the various ways in
                  which <gi>ab</gi> can be used.</p>
               <p n="34">Cases might arise in which pre-printed parts express a date or a location
                  and, therefore, belong in <gi>opener</gi>.<note n="11" xml:id="fn11">E.g. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7925/drs1.ivrla_4071">https://doi.org/10.7925/drs1.ivrla_4071</ref>.</note> When using
                     <gi>ab</gi> for the encoding of pre-printed, typed and handwritten parts, it
                  could make sense to place these encodings within <gi>opener</gi>. Since
                     <gi>ab</gi> is not allowed within <gi>opener</gi>, this is another reason not
                  to use <gi>ab</gi>.</p>
            </div>

            <div xml:id="c-3-2">
               <head xml:id="issue2-2">Issue 2: Using <gi>fw</gi></head>
               <p n="35">The forme work element might be fitting for letterheads with names and
                  addresses, as has already been described in <ref target="#c-2-1">Case 1:
                     Letterheads, issue 1</ref>. However, it seems not applicable for pre-printed
                  parts like forms. First, documents like the field postcard in example 4 do not
                  consist of a running head but the pre-printed text rather occurs on a single page
                  and is, therefore, not a continuous feature. Thus, the definition of <gi>fw</gi>
                  cannot be applied to this case. Second, the type attribute could be used to
                  distinguish between pre-printed, handwritten or typed text, but, analogous to the
                  case in Issue 1, there is no such usage convention of @type in TEI.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-3-3">
               <head xml:id="issue2-3">Issue 3: Using <gi>figure</gi></head>
               <p n="36">The use of <gi>figure</gi> for pre-printed parts has already been discussed
                  letterheads (see <ref target="#c-2-4">Case 1: Letterheads, issue 4</ref>. There
                  are two main reasons why <gi>figure</gi> should not be used for pre-printed text.
                  First of all, such documents as in example 4 do not contain an illustration,
                  formula, or figure in a narrow sense, so using <gi>figure</gi> is excluded due to
                  its definition. Furthermore—as is the case in issue 1: Using <gi>ab</gi> and issue
                  2: Using <gi>fw</gi>—there is no convention in TEI of using the type attribute to
                  express a distinction between handwritten (or typed) and pre-printed text.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-3-4">
               <head xml:id="issue2-4">Issue 4: Using <gi>seg</gi></head>
               <p n="37">The element <gi>seg</gi> marks arbitrary segments within a text. It is
                  designed for the encoder to mark any segmentation of interest.<note n="12" xml:id="fn12"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-seg.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-seg.html</ref>.</note>
                  The attribute–value pairs described in <ref target="#c-3-1">Case 2, issue 1: Using
                        <gi>ab</gi></ref> could be applied to <gi>seg</gi>. Thus, a possible
                  encoding of the field postcard might be done as follows (simplified, deletions by
                  sender not encoded):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ab>
                        <seg type="pre-printed">Absender:</seg>
                        <seg type="handwritten">Vizewachtm. Marc</seg>
                        <seg type="handwritten">Galde<lb/>Fuchs</seg>
                        <seg type="pre-printed">Armeekorps<lb/>Division</seg>
                        <seg type="handwritten"><lb/><lb/>Ersatz</seg>
                        <seg type="pre-printed">Regiment No<lb/>Bataillon<lb/>Abteilung</seg>
                        <seg type="pre-printed">Kompagnie<lb/>Batterie<lb/>Eskadron<lb/>Kolonne</seg>
                        <seg type="pre-printed">Besondere Formationen: (Flieger, Funker usw.)</seg>
                        <seg type="handwritten">Schilling der 1. bayr. Feld-​Art. Rgt. Leichte-​Mun.
                           Kol.</seg>
                     </ab>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="38">There is a clear advantage compared to the usage of <gi>ab</gi>: In the TEI
                  description of <gi>seg</gi>, it is specifically stated that the encoder is free to
                  define his or her own segments of text. But again, as in issue 1: using
                     <gi>ab</gi>, there is no convention in TEI to use @type in order to categorize
                  pre-printed, typed and handwritten text. In addition to that, <gi>seg</gi> is an
                  inline element and therefore cannot be used in the same way as <gi>ab</gi>, for
                  example. The necessity to enclose <gi>seg</gi> with a block element might be
                  problematic.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-3-5">
               <head xml:id="issue2-5">Issue 5: Using <gi>handShift</gi>, and proposal of new
                  element <gi>formShift</gi></head>
               <p n="39">Another possible solution is the use of <gi>handShift</gi>. This turns out
                  to cause problems regarding the definition of <gi>handShift</gi> in the TEI
                  Guidelines:</p>
               <cit>
                  <quote><gi>handShift</gi> marks the beginning of a sequence of text written in a
                     new hand, or the beginning of a scribal stint.</quote>
                  <ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-handShift.html">(https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-handShift.html)</ref>
               </cit>
               <p n="40">As we do not only deal with the shift between different hands but between a
                  hand and a pre-printed form or machine-written part and pre-printed form, the use
                  of <gi>handShift</gi> does not cover all these possible shifts and is, therefore,
                  not an option.</p>
               <p n="41">This is why we propose a new element <gi>formShift</gi>. This new element
                  could then be used at the point of transition from pre-printed text to
                  non-pre-printed text and vice versa. To indicate these different shifts, we would
                  recommend the attribute type with the predefined values handwritten (shift from
                  pre-printed or typed to handwritten), typed (shift from handwritten or pre-printed
                  to typed) and pre-printed (shift from handwritten or typed to pre-printed).
                  Compared to the previous cases, we would have an element created specifically for
                  the task of describing such shifts. The type attribute would then have the sole
                  and specific function to indicate the shifts.</p>
               <p n="42">The description of how the pre-printed parts look like could be encoded in
                     <gi>layoutDesc</gi> as part of <gi>objectDesc</gi>: For example 4, the
                     <gi>layoutDesc</gi> might look like this:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <objectDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <p>Turned 90 degrees to the left, there is pre-printed text combined with
                              dotted lines where handwritten entries were made.</p>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                  </egXML>
               
               <p n="43">Here is a possible solution for example 4, using the suggested element
                     <gi>formShift</gi> (simplified, deletions by sender not encoded):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <objectDesc>
                        <layoutDesc>
                           <p xml:id="pre-printed">Turned 90 degrees to the left, there is
                              pre-printed text combined with dotted lines where handwritten entries
                              were made.</p>
                        </layoutDesc>
                     </objectDesc>
                     <!-- [...] -->
                     <div corresp="#pre-printed">
                        <p>Absender: <formShift type="handwritten"/>Vizewachtm. Marc <lb/>Galde
                           <lb/>Fuchs <formShift type="pre-printed"/>Armeekorps <lb/>Division
                              <formShift type="handwritten"/>
                           <lb/>
                           <lb/>Ersatz <formShift type="pre-printed"/>Regiment No
                           <lb/>Bataillon<lb/>Abteilung <formShift type="handwritten"/>
                           <lb/>
                           <lb/>
                           <formShift type="pre-printed"/>Kompagnie <lb/>Batterie <lb/>Eskadron
                           <lb/>Kolonne </p>
                        <p> Besondere Formationen: (Flieger, Funker usw.) <formShift type="handwritten"/>Schilling der 1. bayr. Feld-​Art. Rgt.
                           Leichte-​Mun. Kol.</p>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               <p n="44">The attribute-value pair corresp="pre-printed" would indicate the linking
                  between the pre-printed text and the description in the meta data.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
               <head>Bibliography</head>
               <listBibl>
                  <bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/TMLGNZ5L">TEI Consortium, ed. 2019. ‟Correspondence Description.ˮ In <hi rendition="#i">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</hi>.
                     Version 3.6.0, 63–65. <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/HD.html#HD44CD</ref>.</bibl>
                  <bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/A3F94BIQ">TEI Consortium, ed. 2019. ‟Headers, Footers, and Similar Matter.ˮ In <hi rendition="#i">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                        Interchange</hi>. Version 3.6.0, 419–420. <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html#PHSK">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html#PHSK</ref>.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>