<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="stamps-seals-postmarks">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Postage stamps, seals, and postmarks</title>
            <author key="obert">Dewi Josephine Obert</author>
            <author key="trautmann">Marjam Trautmann</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>
            <date when="2020-03-05"/>
            <idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200421172336303-8613365-9</idno>
            <idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/stamps-seals-postmarks.html</idno>
            <idno type="zotero">https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/NMRZD7DC</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title type="main">Encoding Correspondence.</title>
            <title type="sub">A manual for encoding letters and postcards in TEI-XML and
               DTABf</title>
            <editor>Stefan Dumont</editor>
            <editor>Susanne Haaf</editor>
            <editor>Sabine Seifert</editor>
            <idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163329488-8695229-7</idno>
            <idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/</idno>
            <biblScope unit="edition">v1</biblScope>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change n="1" when="2020-03-05" status="draft">Initial Version</change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="c-1">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p n="1">Next to addresses and pre-printed parts, a topic that often seems to be neglected
               within the TEI universe are the additional parts of information found on envelopes or
               postcards, like stamps, seals, and postmarks. Seals are specifically chosen by the
               sender and, thus, can tell us a lot about them. Postmarks and postage stamps,
               however, seem to be quite the opposite—the sender exerts little to no influence on
               both. Still, they can contain a great deal of information about the time and location
               the letter was sent from. Furthermore, many tourist spots will have their well-known
               places, sights, or buildings printed on their stamps. Even postmarks can include
               special editions for certain anniversaries or other festivities. If these elements
               are not included, a lot of relevant information about the document in question could
               be missed.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="c-2">
            <head>Postage stamps</head>
            <div xml:id="c-2-1">
               <p n="2">The TEI Guidelines do list an element called <gi>stamp</gi> that "<quote>contains
                     a word or phrase describing a stamp or similar device</quote>"<note n="1" xml:id="fn1"><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-stamp.html">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-stamp.html</ref>.
                  </note>. This element, however, usually refers to armorial stamps or rubber
                  stamps. But when encoding envelopes or postcards, taking postal stamps into
                  consideration is often inevitable.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 1: Postcard with stamps (source: Swiss-German picture postcard
                     corpus ANKO, <ref target="https://www.ds.uzh.ch/de/projekte/ansichtskartenprojekt">https://www.ds.uzh.ch/de/projekte/ansichtskartenprojekt/</ref>).</head>
                  <graphic url="../images/stamps-seals-postmarks/example1.png"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-2">
               <head>Approach 1: Postage stamps within the <gi>text</gi> element</head>
               <p n="3">If the stamps are to be included within the <gi>text</gi> element, a suitable
                  encoding might be the use of the <gi>figure</gi> element with a @type, such as
                     <gi>figure</gi> type="postage-stamp". However, it has to be noted that the
                  given definition is not really what we are looking for: "<quote><gi>figure</gi>
                     groups elements representing or containing graphic information such as an
                     illustration, formula, or figure</quote>"<note n="2" xml:id="fn2"><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-figure.html">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-figure.html</ref>.
                  </note>.</p>
               <p n="4">As mentioned above, the element <gi>stamp</gi> does already exist but is rather
                  used for rubber stamps. A convenient addition could therefore be the expansion of
                  the description and usage of the <gi>stamp</gi> element to include postal stamps
                  as well.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-3">
               <head>Approach 2: Postage stamps within the meta data</head>
               <p n="5">Understanding postage stamps as part of the meta data could be another proposal.
                  An adequate place to put them could be the <gi>objectType</gi> element, for
                  example within the <gi>physDesc</gi> element. This way it can be stated that one
                  or several stamps are present in the given document. It is also easily possible to
                  add the text written on the stamp, as well as any other information required such
                  as the motive or value.</p>
               <p n="6">A possible encoding of example 1 might look like this: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <msDesc>
                        <physDesc>
                           <p><idno type="postcard">101030</idno>
                              <objectType n="1">Stamp</objectType> from Italy with the imprint
                                 <quote>CASTELLO <lb/> ARAGONESE • ISCHIA 100<lb/> ITALIA</quote>
                              <figure>
                                 <graphic url="postagestamp1.jpg"/>
                                 <figDesc>The drawing on the postage stamp shows a castle on top of
                                    a cliff.</figDesc>
                              </figure>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <objectType n="2">Stamp</objectType> from Italy with the imprint
                                 <quote>CASTELLO <lb/> SCALIGERO • SIRMIONE 600<lb/> ITALIA</quote>
                              <figure>
                                 <graphic url="postagestamp2.jpg"/>
                                 <figDesc>The drawing on the postage stamp shows a castle next to a
                                    body of water</figDesc>
                              </figure>
                           </p>
                        </physDesc>
                     </msDesc>
                  </egXML></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-2-4">
               <head>Postage stamps: Conclusion</head>
               <p n="7">By the current status, there is no uncomplicated way to incorporate postage stamps
                  inside the <gi>text</gi> element. It also seems unnecessary to invent a new
                  element specifically for those—considering that a <gi>stamp</gi> element already
                  exists. Therefore the proposal to solve this problem would either be to expand the
                  description and usage of the <gi>stamp</gi> element to include postal stamps as
                  well, or to just position them in the <gi>physDesc</gi> element within the
                  metadata, where it is possible to add significant information such as the text or
                  motive.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="c-3">
            <head>Seals</head>
            <div xml:id="c-3-1">
               <p n="8">A similar issue is the topic of seals: There is the option to encode them in the
                  header via <gi>sealDesc</gi> (within <gi>physDesc</gi>), which "<quote>describes
                     the seals or similar items related to the object described</quote>"<note n="3" xml:id="fn3"><ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-sealDesc.html">http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-sealDesc.html</ref>.</note>. It is even possible to specify the @type and @subtype of the seal
                  as well as describing it along with other desired information such as the date,
                  owner and a description.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 2: Seal on an envelope for a letter (source: Clara Schumann to
                     Hedwig von Holstein, 18 June 1886, <ref target="https://www.deutsche-digitale-bibliothek.de/item/SD5BCK2IF4HNMI5AYZHYDRD4YIOZJ6S7">https://www.deutsche-digitale-bibliothek.de/item/SD5BCK2IF4HNMI5AYZHYDRD4YIOZJ6S7</ref>).</head>
                  <graphic url="../images/stamps-seals-postmarks/example2.png"/>
               </figure>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><physDesc>
                     <sealDesc>
                        <seal type="x" subtype="y">
                           <p>Round seal of <name>XY</name> made of red wax</p>
                        </seal>
                     </sealDesc>
                  </physDesc>
               </egXML>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 3: Three seals on a letter (source: Adelbert von Chamisso to Louis
                     de La Foye, 26 June 1804, <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief005ChamissoandeLaFoye+en#2">https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/manuscript?Brief005ChamissoandeLaFoye+en#2</ref>).</head>
                  <graphic url="../images/stamps-seals-postmarks/example3.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p n="9">A possible encoding of the seals in example 3 might look like this:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><physDesc>
                     <sealDesc>
                        <seal n="1">
                           <p>The green wax seal represents the motto of the "Nordsternbund":
                                 <foreign xml:lang="grc"><hi rend="greek">τὸ του πόλοῦ
                                 ἄστρον</hi></foreign>.</p>
                        </seal>
                        <seal n="2">
                           <p>The red wax seal has not been identified yet.</p>
                        </seal>
                        <seal n="3">
                           <p>The yellow wax seal shows Chinese inscriptions. In his book "Reise um
                              die Welt" (p. 132), Chamisso reports that Julius Klaproth gave him
                              that seal in 1804 or 1805 and that it shows a quote by Confucius.</p>
                        </seal>
                     </sealDesc>
                  </physDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p n="10">Such an encoding is both sufficient and reasonable, and putting the encoding of
                  seals within the <gi>text</gi> element can be dismissed. Seals, just as postage
                  stamps, do not really belong to the text flow and, therefore, do not need an
                  element of their own within the text. If insisted upon, the element
                     <gi>figure</gi> should be adequate (again, example 3):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><text>
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <figure type="seal" n="1">
                              <graphic url="seal1.jpg"/>
                              <figDesc>A green wax seal, representing the motto of the
                                 "Nordsternbund": <foreign xml:lang="grc"><hi rend="greek">τὸ του
                                       πόλοῦ ἄστρον</hi></foreign>.</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                           <figure type="seal" n="2">
                              <graphic url="seal2.jpg"/>
                              <figDesc>A red wax seal that has not been identified yet.</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                           <figure type="seal" n="3">
                              <graphic url="seal3.jpg"/>
                              <figDesc>A yellow wax seal that shows Chinese inscriptions. In his
                                 book "Reise um die Welt" (p. 132), Chamisso reports that Julius
                                 Klaproth gave him that seal in 1804 or 1805 and that it shows a
                                 quote by Confucius</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </egXML>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="c-4">
            <head>Postmarks</head>
            <div xml:id="c-4-1">
               <p n="11">Postmarks provide information about the place and date of shipping of the letter.
                  This information can be found in the <gi>correspAction</gi> element of the
                     <gi>teiHeader</gi>. Furthermore, it is thinkable, depending on the question,
                  that one would like to explicitly refer to the existence of a postmark and its
                  information content. Also a differentiation between the date and place of the
                  letter written by the sender, on the one hand, and the date and place at which the
                  letter was actually dispatched by the post office, on the other hand, could be
                  relevant. In the following, it is assumed that the letter writer provided
                  handwritten information. This is usually encoded within <gi>text</gi> within
                     <gi>dateline</gi> and can also be found in <gi>correspAction</gi>. However, the
                  postmark might provide different information. If there is a correct date of
                  dispatch, i.e. the date on the postmark, this is always encoded in
                     <gi>correspDesc</gi>. It should be recorded elsewhere in the metadata, if the
                  handwritten date differs from the date documented on the postmark.</p>
               <p n="12">Such a case could be encoded in the element <gi>origin</gi> within the element
                     <gi>history</gi>. According to the TEI P5 Guidelines, <gi>history</gi>
                     "<quote>groups elements describing the full history of a manuscript, manuscript
                     part, or other object</quote>"<note n="4" xml:id="fn4"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-history.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-history.html</ref>.
                  </note> and being part of it, <gi>origin</gi> "<quote>contains any descriptive or
                     other information concerning the origin of a manuscript, manuscript part, or
                     other object</quote>"<note n="5" xml:id="fn5"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-origin.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-origin.html</ref>.
                  </note>. The reference to a handwritten date would reflect the course of the
                  origin of the letter at this point. As another possibility we would like to
                  suggest the encoding of the handwritten date as <gi>note</gi> within the
                  respective <gi>correspAction</gi>. Both suggestions are presented in the
                  fictitious example below.</p>
               <p n="13">Encoding example within the <gi>history</gi> element:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <sourceDesc>
                     <msDesc>
                        <history>
                           <origin>
                              <p>The sender dates the letter, contrary to the postmark, to the
                                    <origDate when="1915-01-16">16 January 1915</origDate>.</p>
                           </origin>
                        </history>
                     </msDesc>
                  </sourceDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p n="14">Encoding example within <gi>correspAction</gi>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><correspDesc>
                     <correspAction type="sent">
                        <persName>Franz Marc</persName>
                        <placeName>Benediktbeuern</placeName>
                        <date when="1915-01-18"/>
                        <note>The sender dates the letter, contrary to the postmark, to the
                              <origDate when="1915-01-16">16 January 1915</origDate>.</note>
                     </correspAction>
                     <correspAction type="received">
                        <!-- [...] -->
                     </correspAction>
                  </correspDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p n="15">Another possibility would be the separate encoding of the postmark. In the
                  following, we would like to discuss possible coding variants using example 4:</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Example 4: Postcard with several stamps (source: Franz Marc to Herwarth
                     Walden, 16 January 1915, in: DER STURM. Digitale Quellenedition zur Geschichte
                     der internationalen Avantgarde, <ref target="https://sturm-​edition.de/id/Q.01.19150116.FMA.01">https://sturm-​edition.de/id/Q.01.19150116.FMA.01</ref>).</head>
                  <graphic url="../images/stamps-seals-postmarks/example4.png"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-4-2">
               <head>Approach 1: Postmarks within the meta data</head>
               <p n="16">A postmark is not an object in the true sense of the word, like a stamp or a seal.
                  However, the definition of the <gi>stamp</gi> element in the TEI Guidelines states
                  that it could also represent a "<quote>similar device</quote>"<note n="6" xml:id="fn6"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-stamp.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-stamp.html</ref>.
                  </note>—something to which a postmark could be assigned. As an equivalent to
                  stamps, it would therefore be conceivable to encode postmarks within the
                     <gi>teiHeader</gi> in <gi>msDesc</gi> as <gi>stamp</gi> and, in addition to a
                  description, to encode the stamped information of example 4 as follows or
                  similarly:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><msDesc>
                     <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                           <supportDesc>
                              <support>
                                 <p>postcard with
                                             postmark:<stamp><!-- Description if needed--><mentioned><placeName>Feldpoststation
                                             A. A. Falkenhausen</placeName><date when="1915-01-18">18 Januar 15</date>2-3 N</mentioned></stamp></p>
                              </support>
                           </supportDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                     </physDesc>
                  </msDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p n="17"><gi>support</gi> "<quote>contains a description of the materials etc. which make
                     up the physical support for the written part of a manuscript or other
                     object</quote>"<note n="7" xml:id="fn7"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-support.html">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-support.html</ref>.
                  </note>—a definition that could include postmarks. Furthermore, the TEI P5
                  Guidelines recommend to clearly separate the transcription of text written on an
                  object from the editor’s description of that object, e.g. by <gi>mentioned</gi>
                  for the text of stamps as child element of <gi>stamp</gi><note n="8" xml:id="fn8"><ref target="https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#mswat">https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html#mswat</ref>.
                  </note>. The element <gi>mentioned</gi>, however, is intended to make words and
                  phrases explicit that are only implicit in the text: "<quote><gi>mentioned</gi>
                     marks words or phrases mentioned, not used</quote>"<note n="9" xml:id="fn9"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/de/html/ref-mentioned.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/de/html/ref-mentioned.html</ref>.
                  </note>. This appears to be a contradiction within the TEI Guidelines. Elements
                  like <gi>q</gi>, <gi>quote</gi> and <gi>cit</gi> are not allowed at this point,
                  perhaps a validation of these elements at this point would be the resolution of
                  the discrepancy we suspect for the element <gi>mentioned</gi>?</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-4-3">
               <head>Approach 2: Postmarks within the <gi>text</gi> element</head>
               <p n="18">For encoding the postmark within the <gi>text</gi> element, we suggest using a
                  typified <gi>ab</gi> or <gi>div</gi> element (the latter needing an additional
                     <gi>p</gi>):</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><ab type="postmark"><placeName>Feldpoststation A.A. Falkenhausen</placeName><date>18 Januar
                        15</date></ab></egXML>
               <p n="19">or</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="postmark">
                     <p>
                        <placeName>Feldpoststation A.A. Falkenhausen</placeName>
                        <date>18 Januar 15</date>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <p n="20">Within <gi>text</gi> non-encoded descriptions in plain text of objects in the
                  letter—to which a postmark is counted here—are not provided per se, and are rather
                  assigned to the metadata in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>. So <gi>stamp</gi>, if you want
                  to use it correctly, must not be used within <gi>text</gi> since the element
                     <gi>stamp</gi> explicitly contains a description of the object and is solely
                  part of <gi>msDesc</gi>. But would not a valid use of the <gi>stamp</gi>
                  element—in combination with a validation of elements like <gi>cit</gi>,
                     <gi>quote</gi> etc. as discussed in approach 1—also make sense within
                     <gi>body</gi>, not only for postmarks but also for other types of stamps (e.g.
                  for receipt stamps)?</p>
               <p n="21">Another solution could be to encode the actual letter text again separately in a
                     <gi>div</gi> or <gi>ab</gi> element, or to even introduce a new element
                     <gi>postmark</gi> within the <gi>text</gi> element.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body>
                     <ab type="postmark">
                        <placeName>A.A. Falkenhausen</placeName>
                        <date>18 Januar 15</date>
                     </ab>
                     <div>
                        <opener/>
                        <!-- [...] -->
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </egXML>
               <p n="22">or</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body>
                     <postmark>
                        <placeName>A.A. Falkenhausen</placeName>
                        <date>18 Januar 15</date>
                     </postmark>
                     <opener/>
                     <!-- [...] -->
                  </body>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="c-4-4">
               <head>Postmarks: Conclusion</head>
               <p n="23">To take into account the difference between handwritten places and dates and those
                  on postmarks in the coding of correspondence, we discussed different approaches.
                  In order to document the handwritten date in the meta data, we suggest using the
                  element <gi>origin</gi> within <gi>history</gi>/<gi>msDesc</gi>, or analogously an
                  additional <gi>note</gi> within <gi>correspAction</gi>, since the date of the
                  postmark is always listed in the <gi>correspAction</gi>.</p>
               <p n="24">However, in order to capture the information of the postmark not only in terms of
                  content but also in terms of a transcription, we make two suggestions. The first
                  is the possible encoding of the text of the postmark in the element <gi>stamp</gi>
                  within <gi>support</gi> (inside <gi>msDesc</gi>) (approach1). Here, the explicit
                  text is in the element <gi>mentioned</gi>, which contradicts the actual definition
                  of this element. For this reason, we suggest allowing elements such as
                     <gi>cit</gi>, <gi>quote</gi>, and <gi>q</gi> in the <gi>stamp</gi> element.</p>
               <p n="25">In our second approach, we discussed the possibilities of encoding the postmark
                  within <gi>text</gi>. One way could be to use a paragraph-like element like
                     <gi>ab</gi> or <gi>div</gi> with a @type attribute "postmark". We also
                  encourage discussion on the possibility of introducing a separate element
                     <gi>postmark</gi> or to validate <gi>stamp</gi> with the adjustments proposed
                  in approach 1 for elements such as <gi>cit</gi>, <gi>q</gi> and
                  <gi>quote</gi>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>