<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="uncertainties-metadata">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Uncertainties in metadata</title>
				<author key="daengeli">Peter Dängeli</author>
				<author key="hoedl-notter">Isabella Hödl-Notter</author>
				<author key="steyer">Timo Steyer</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities</publisher>
				<date when="2020-08-24"/>
				<idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200824161745822-9539282-1</idno>
				<idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/uncertainties-metadata.html</idno>
				<idno type="zotero">https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/KEX2RSUX</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title type="main">Encoding Correspondence.</title>
				<title type="sub">A manual for encoding letters and postcards in TEI-XML and
					DTABf</title>
				<editor>Stefan Dumont</editor>
				<editor>Susanne Haaf</editor>
				<editor>Sabine Seifert</editor>
				<idno type="urn">urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4-20200110163329488-8695229-7</idno>
				<idno type="url">https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1/</idno>
				<biblScope unit="edition">v1</biblScope>
			</seriesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Born digital.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<listChange>
				<change n="1" when="2020-08-24" status="draft">Initial Version</change>
			</listChange>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="c-1">
				<head>Introduction</head>
				<p n="1">Uncertainties are a common challenge in scholarly work. It is fundamentally
					important to point out uncertainties in order to make the research process and
					the results transparent and comprehensible. In contrast to natural sciences
					(e.g. mathematics), the humanities often miss the opportunity to model
					uncertainties exactly. The handling of uncertainties, especially when working
					with historical sources, is therefore usually explained descriptively—so far,
					however, lacking a best practice regarding the retention of uncertainties or
					decision-making in digital editions.<note n="1" xml:id="fn1">Regarding
						graph-based modeling of uncertainties: Kuczera, Andreas, Wübbena, Thorsten,
						and Thomas Kollatz (eds.). 2019. Die Modellierung des Zweifels —
						Schlüsselideen und -konzepte zur graphbasierten Modellierung von
						Unsicherheiten. Wolfenbüttel. (Zeitschrift für digitale
						Geisteswissenschaften / Sonderbände, 4). DOI: 10.17175/sb004.</note></p>
				<p n="2">Basically, editors face three challenges: First, uncertainties must be
					identified, second, they must be modelled/made comprehensible, and third, they
					must be commented on or interpreted by the editor. These steps must be taken
					into account in the creation of editions—not only in the main text but also in
					the metadata. The importance of metadata is significant for proof and
					transparency of research, for findability, distribution and interlinking as well
					as for their obvious potential for evaluation methods (e.g. network
					visualizations).</p>
				<p n="3">The core idea of metadata lies in having a simple and accurate data set that
					summarizes the most important information about the particular information
					resource. Metadata has been playing an increasingly important role in the
					research process for some time, and also has become a subject of research in its
					own right.</p>
				<p n="4">Good metadata facilitates interoperability. Describing/mapping uncertainties in
					metadata does not necessarily impede this. The goal must therefore be to
					identify uncertainties but not to fall back to project- or case-specific
					solutions or data models; otherwise, such an approach threatens the accuracy of
					scientific research as well as the prospect of interoperability. Precision of
					the metadata with regard to the disclosure of uncertainties is therefore
					urgently needed.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="c-2">
				<head>Modelling uncertainties in the TEI</head>
				<p n="5">In principle, the TEI guidelines take into account two types of uncertainties: On
					the one hand, uncertainty regarding the use of the appropriate TEI element and,
					on the other hand, uncertain ways of reading text passages/words or the
					identification of entities like persons or places. Both areas offer
					opportunities to highlight uncertainty regarding entities.</p>
				<p n="6">This article concentrates on uncertain readings as well as dealing with various
					forms of supplementary information.<note n="2" xml:id="fn2">The use of the
						correct TEI element will need to be discussed elsewhere.</note> For the
					encoding of insecure readings and related information, the chapters 11.3.3.2 and
					21 of the TEI Guidelines are of relevance (Chapter 11.3.3.2 "Use of the
						<gi>gap</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>, and
						<gi>supplied</gi> Elements in Combination";<note n="3" xml:id="fn3"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html#PHST">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/PH.html#PHST</ref></note>
					Chapter 21 "Certainty, Precision, and Responsibility"<note n="4" xml:id="fn4"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CE.html">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CE.html</ref></note>).
					When modelling uncertainty, it is essential to specify the responsibility
						(<att>resp</att> or <gi>respons</gi>), the degree of uncertainty
						(<att>cert</att>, <att>precision</att>) and the reason (<att>reason</att> or
					via <gi>note</gi>) in order to make the decisions comprehensible for readers.
					For this purpose, a gradual encoding of uncertainty is possible using
						<att>cert</att> with fixed values (high, medium, low, unknown). This area
					seems to be well covered by the existing possibilities.</p>
				<p n="7">However, problems arise when uncertainties in metadata are to be modelled and
					these relate primarily to entities and datings. As we observe, there is a
					certain arbitrariness in the encodings, which may be a signal of inadequate
					documentation or uncertainty in dealing with the current guidelines. Certainly,
					the described characteristics of metadata (see introduction) also play a
					role.</p>
				<p n="8">This impression was reinforced by the discussions and the examples presented in
					the workshop preceding this handbook on encoding correspondence. The aim of this
					contribution is to inform about existing possibilities, to give examples as well
					as to address some existing gaps and to develop coding suggestions.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="c-3">
				<head>General challenges</head>
				<p n="9">The challenges of modelling uncertainties of metadata are an integral part of
					every modelling process in the humanities and accompany editorial projects as
					well as database-driven development or cataloging projects. The fundamental
					dilemma in this context is the requirement of metadata for information that is
					as granular, structured and standardized as possible, and the widespread
					approach of researchers to enter information that circumscribes uncertainty or
					to restrict themselves to one of several possible entities. Typical forms are
					"around 1700", "Late Middle Ages", or "located between Cologne and Dusseldorf".
					Thus, regardless of the following recommendations, it is necessary to understand
					the relevance of metadata for automated processing steps, i.e. for further
					processing of the data in search portals or interfaces. Only if the researchers
					become aware of this and are willing to engage in structured and standardized
					information input in the metadata, also with respect to uncertainties, the
					quality of metadata dealing with uncertainties may sustainably be improved.</p>
				<p n="10">Another challenge is the often unsatisfactory authority data. The use of
					authority data is a key factor in ensuring that metadata is reusable. In
					particular, authority data can be used to identify entities in the metadata with
					added value but there is often a lack of differentiating information in the
					authority data. To give one example, authority datasets do not include
					identifiers for all territorial units. While there is a GeoNames identifier for
					today's state of Bavaria (2951839),<note n="5" xml:id="fn5"><ref target="http://www.geonames.org/2951839">http://www.geonames.org/2951839</ref></note> identifiers describing the
					electorate, duchy, or the scale of the early modern Upper and Lower Bavaria are
					missing. While authority data are used to uniquely identify an entity, they
					cannot be seen in the same way as content-rich biographical reference works or
					lexicons but the combination of an authority record with incomplete or
					non-scientific information poses a problem here. The only remedy is the insight
					that norm data serve primarily for identification and only secondarily for
					description.</p>
				<p n="11">Thus, in order to model uncertainties in metadata, one needs to be aware,
					firstly, of the benefits of metadata and the fact that they are not suitable for
					mapping all possible interpretive variants, and, secondly, the perspective on
					norm data as a reliable means of identification and less as a resource for
					further information.</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="c-4">
				<head>Recommendations for coding uncertainties</head>
				<p n="12">In the metadata, uncertainties occur at almost any location where information
					from the source is recorded. If a source document is undated, multi-dated, or
					ambivalently dated, such as being ambiguous about the underlying calendar,
					editors feel compelled to identify the most plausible date and assign it to the
					source. Likewise, location information may be missing or may not be specified
					with sufficient accuracy. For instance, the resolution of an abbreviation may
					not be unique, the same place names may occur in different areas, or historical
					places or field names are no longer common. Similar problems arise with regard
					to the identification of senders and recipients.</p>
				<p n="13">As general recommendations for the coding of uncertainties in metadata we suggest
					the following general rules:<lb/>
					<list rend="numbered">
						<item n="1">Always identify uncertainties in the metadata; the recognition,
							identification and interpretation of uncertainties is a scientific
							achievement,</item>
						<item n="2">Render the process of coding transparent by indicating who is
							responsible for encoding the uncertainty,</item>
						<item n="3">Distinguish whether the uncertainty is source-related (intrinsic) or
							based on inaccurate or ambiguous identification options
							(extrinsic),</item>
						<item n="4">Name methods (<att>evidence</att> with recommended values "internal",
							"external", and "conjecture") to make transparent in which way the
							uncertainty was resolved,</item>
						<item n="5">If possible, refer to external references (authority data,
							prosopographic databases, etc.) in order to give researchers the
							opportunity to familiarize themselves with the phenomenon at
							hand,</item>
						<item n="6">If possible, add indications on how to process the information for
							analytical and indexing purposes.</item>
					</list></p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="c-5">
				<head>What about degrees of uncertainty?</head>
				<p n="14">Apart from these general recommendations, the question of whether the degree of
					uncertainty should be encoded is a matter which researchers always have to
					answer anew for each edition project as there are until now no common guidelines
					or best practice models. The most straightforward answer to this question is the
					statement that an indication is either certain or uncertain and therefore
					establishing a degree of uncertainty is a far too subjective undertaking.<note n="6" xml:id="fn6">It is possible to encode the degree of uncertainty using
						the values ​​"low", "medium" or "high". Some edition projects employ a more
						specific indication using percentage.</note> In our opinion, it would be
					advisable to dispense with the specification of granularity in the metadata and
					to state only generally whether the information is secure or uncertain. The
					(implicit) default specification reasonably being <att>cert</att>="true", the
					statement <att>cert</att>="false" would only need to be set in cases of
					uncertainty. However, this would require a corresponding change in the content
					model of <hi>teidata.certainty</hi>, which introduces these Boolean values as
					alternatives to the existing options (in order to allow for backward
					compatibility). To remain in line with the current options offered by the TEI,
					projects might provide an indication whether <att>cert</att>="medium" shall be
					evaluated as certain or uncertain by applications that distinguish only these
					two statuses (with "unknown" and "low" defaulting to uncertainty and "high"
					defaulting to certainty).</p>
			</div>
			<div xml:id="c-6">
				<head>Examples of uncertain information and proposed solutions</head>
				<p n="15">Strategies for dealing with uncertainty often include the recording of different
					options and their evaluation for plausibility and possibly mutual compatibility.
					There is a need to record possible alternatives and to assign a priority to at
					least one of them, pursuing the goal to maintain transparency and select a "best
					option". This prioritised option may then be considered by default in the
					processing of metadata (such as inclusion in registers, search indices, etc.).
					In Chapter 16.8 "Alternation", the TEI offers several basic approaches on how to
					capture and prioritise alternatives.<note n="7" xml:id="fn7"><ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SAAT">https://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SA.html#SAAT</ref></note></p>
				<p n="16">One such mechanism is the <hi>select</hi> attribute (see the following
					explication), which allows one or more of the detected alternatives to be
					specified starting from a hierarchically superior element (in the form of
					space-separated <hi>tei.pointers</hi>). Because <att>select</att> mostly refers
					to identifiers (<att>xml:id</att>), this procedure is well suited for the
					recognition of named entities such as places or persons. For time units such as
					dates or periods of time we are more reluctant to use <att>xml:id</att> and
					prefer the use of <att>select</att> in combination with <att>n</att> or
						<att>ana</att>. This offers the possibility to provide more detailed
					descriptions. The evaluation of <att>select</att> would thus use not one
					specific but two different reference schemes, which is not very elegant and
					presents additional challenges for processing routines. The appropriate schema
					would either need to depend on a <att>type</att> or be based on the syntactic
					structure of the pointer.</p>
				<p n="17">An alternative approach to referencing specific metadata is local tagging
					directly at each element. This approach seems to be more consistent. At the same
					time it facilitates clarity and data processing. This kind of marking can be
					done explicitly (e.g. via <att>ana</att>) but it can also be done implicitly by
					creating just one element of each type—carrying the information that is deemed
					most precise or probable—directly within <gi>correspAction</gi> and specifying
					all alternative places, persons and data only at a deeper level. Using this
					approach, only one place of dispatch, address, recipient and sender as well as a
					date of dispatch and date of receipt would be specified directly within
						<gi>correspAction</gi> and more detailed and possibly alternative
					information might be located in <gi>note</gi> elements, (partially) structured
					or in prose. Given that letters may be written and sent by more than one person
					from and to more than one place and at more than one date, it is hardly possible
					to narrow the schema to allow only one element of each type directly within
						<gi>correspAction</gi>.<note n="8" xml:id="fn8">For dates, it has been
						suggested to narrow the CMIF schema to allow just one date. Cf. <ref target="https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF/issues/19">https://github.com/TEI-Correspondence-SIG/CMIF/issues/19</ref>.</note>
					Thus we can only suggest a best practice but not enforce it formally.</p>
				<div xml:id="c-6-1">
					<head>Dates</head>
					<p n="18">The following examples of uncertain dating show how this kind of hierarchical
						priorisation might be encoded. For each example, we present the nested way
						that demotes alternatives to a lower level as well as a flat encoding where
						alternatives are distinguished using <att>select</att>.</p>
					<div xml:id="c-6-1-1">
						<head>Dating by the editor</head>
						<div xml:id="c-1-1-1">
							<head>Phenomenon: Differing information in secondary literature</head>
							<p n="19">Implementation:</p>
							<figure>
								<head>Example 1: Albrecht von Haller to Giovanni Battista Morgagni,
									Bern, 20 April 1753 (Editions- und Forschungsplattform
									hallerNet, <ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_15556">https://hallernet.org/letter_15556</ref>).</head>
								<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] 
	<date resp="#editor-XY" when="1753-04-20"/>
	<note>Bei <bibl>B2462</bibl> wird 1750 als Jahr angegeben,
	was aber inhaltlich nicht stimmen kann (1750 AVH nicht
	in Bern; die angekündigte Rückkehr nach Göttingen, falls
	er in Bern kein Amt erhält, passt auf Ende April
	1753).</note>
</correspAction></egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="20">Explication: A different date from secondary literature is rated as
								implausible in a comment. Because there is no direct connection with
								the source, the alternative date is not recorded in a structured
								form.</p>
							<p n="21">Alternative implementation (several <gi>date</gi> elements in
									<gi>correspAction</gi>):</p>
							<figure>
								<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref"> [...] 
	<date resp="#editor-XY" when="1753-04-20" n="date_pref"/>
	<date resp="#author-B2462" when="1750" n="date_alt1">
		<note>Bei <bibl>B2462</bibl> wird 1750 als Jahr
		angegeben, was aber inhaltlich nicht stimmen kann
		(1750 AVH nicht in Bern; die angekündigte Rückkehr
		nach Göttingen, falls er in Bern kein Amt erhält,
		passt auf Ende April 1753).</note>
	</date>
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="22">Here and in the following examples, <att>ana</att>="date_alt1" might
								be used instead of <att>n</att>="date_alt1".</p>
						</div>
						<div xml:id="c-1-1-2">
							<head>Phenomena: Insecure reading and correction by the editor; multiple
								dating (two calendars)</head>
							<p n="23">Implementation:</p>
							<figure>
								<head>Example 2: Pierre-François Martin to Albrecht von Haller,
									Lausanne, 21 April 1729 (Editions- und Forschungsplattform
									hallerNet, <ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_04933">https://hallernet.org/letter_04933</ref>).</head>
								<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] 
	<date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="conjecture" when="1729-04-21">
		<note type="evidence">ohne Jahr, eindeutig 1729; Notiz
		von AvH: "du 19 d'avril, reçu le 22"; AvH hat einen
		Rechnungsfehler begangen, 11. ante Kal. Maij ist der
		21.4.</note>
	</date>
	<note type="alternativeDate">
		<date calendar="#roman">11. ante Kalend. Maij</date>
		<p>Die Lesung II. ante Kal. Maij kann nicht stimmen.</p>
	</note> [...] 
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="24">Explication: The letter date is Roman but was incorrectly converted
								in a contemporary note. The editor has determined the appropriate
								date and entered it as regular metadata. He assesses a possible but
								incorrect reading of the Roman date in an additional remark.</p>
							<p n="25">Alternative implementation (several <gi>date</gi> elements in
									<gi>correspAction</gi>):</p>
							<figure>
								<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref"> [...] 
	<date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="conjecture" when="1729-04-21" n="date_pref">
		<note type="evidence">ohne Jahr, eindeutig 1729; Notiz
		von AvH: "du 19 d'avril, reçu le 22"; AvH hat einen
		Rechnungsfehler begangen, 11. ante Kal. Maij ist der
		21.4.</note>
	</date>
	<date calendar="#roman" n="date_alt1">11. ante Kalend. Maij
		<note>die Lesung II. ante Kal. Maij kann nicht
		stimmen</note></date> [...]
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
						</div>
						<div xml:id="c-1-1-3">
							<head>Phenomenon: Date determination from the letter content, intrinsic
								and extrinsic; multiple dating (Julian and Gregorian
								calendar)</head>
							<p n="26">Implementation:</p>
							<figure>
								<head>Example 3: Pietro Orteschi to Albrecht von Haller, Venice, 1st
									May 1768 (Editions- und Forschungsplattform hallerNet, <ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_06362">https://hallernet.org/letter_06362</ref>).</head>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] 
	<date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="internal external conjecture" when="1768-05-01">
		<note type="evidence">Ohne Jahr; Jahr gemäss alter
			Sign., <bibl>GEH</bibl> und Inhalt (O. schickt den
			dritten, vierten und fünften Band seiner
			Zeitschrift, die AvH dann ab dem 13.4.1769 in den
			GGA rezensiert. Wie AvH dort schreibt, umfasst Bd. 5
			die späten Monate von 1766 und den ersten von 1767.
			Da er erwähnt, dass der 6. Band (der also die
			späteren Monate von 1767 und den ersten von 1768
			enthalten sollte) leider noch nicht fertig sei, muss
			der Brief (wie auch bei Thormann angegeben) 1768 zu
			datieren sein).</note>
			<note type="alternativeDate">
				<date calendar="roman">Cal.Maij</date>
			</note>
	</date> [...] 
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="27">The date of the incompletely dated letter was determined by the
								editor from the letter content and in accordance with an old
								signature, whereby the derivation of content is described relatively
								extensively for better traceability. The absence of <att>cert</att>
								indicates that the editor is safe in dating.</p>
							<p n="28">Alternative implementation (several <gi>date</gi> elements in
									<gi>correspAction</gi>):</p>
							<figure>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref"> [...] 
	<date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="internal external conjecture" when="1768-05-01" n="date_pref">
		<note type="evidence">Ohne Jahr; Jahr gemäss alter
			Sign., <bibl>GEH</bibl> und Inhalt (O. schickt den
			dritten, vierten und fünften Band seiner
			Zeitschrift, die AvH dann ab dem 13.4.1769 in den
			GGA rezensiert. Wie AvH dort schreibt, umfasst Bd. 5
			die späten Monate von 1766 und den ersten von 1767.
			Da er erwähnt, dass der 6. Band (der also die
			späteren Monate von 1767 und den ersten von 1768
			enthalten sollte) leider noch nicht fertig sei, muss
			der Brief (wie auch bei Thormann angegeben) 1768 zu
			datieren sein).</note>
	</date>
	<date calendar="roman" n="date_alt1">Cal.Maij</date> [...]
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
						</div>
						<div xml:id="c-1-1-4">
							<head>Factual corrections by the editor</head>
							<p n="29">Implementation:</p>
							<figure>
								<head>Example 4: Jean-Chrysostome de Creyssent to Albrecht von
									Haller, Paris, 24 December 1777 (Editions- und
									Forschungsplattform hallerNet, <ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_01214">https://hallernet.org/letter_01214</ref>).</head>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] <date resp="#editor-XY" cert="high" evidence="conjecture" when="1777-12-24">
		<note type="evidence">Eindeutig als 1771 zu lesen. 1771
			jedoch nicht möglich, da im Brief der
			<bibl>Usong</bibl> (dt. 1771, frz. 1772) und der
			<bibl>Alfrzed</bibl> (dt. 1773, frz. 1775) erwähnt
			werden. Auch erhält C., der als Chan. de Brioude
			unterschreibt, diese Funktion erst 1775. Also wohl
			doch 1777 (wie bei <bibl>GEH</bibl>), dafür spricht
			auch die alte Signatur. [hs/1/96]</note>
	</date> [...] 
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="30">Explication: The example describes the content correction of a
								factually wrong date by the editor. The evidence emerging from the
								source and the historical context is described in a note.</p>
							<p n="31">Alternative implementation (several <gi>date</gi> elements in
									<gi>correspAction</gi>):</p>
							<figure>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref"> [...] <date resp="#editor-XY" cert="true" evidence="conjecture" when="1777-12-24" n="date_pref">
		<note type="evidence">Eindeutig als 1771 zu lesen. 1771
			jedoch nicht möglich, da im Brief der
			<bibl>Usong</bibl> (dt. 1771, frz. 1772) und der
			<bibl>Alfrzed</bibl> (dt. 1773, frz. 1775) erwähnt
			werden. Auch erhält C., der als Chan. de Brioude
			unterschreibt, diese Funktion erst 1775. Also wohl
			doch 1777 (wie bei <bibl>GEH</bibl>), dafür spricht
			auch die alte Signatur. [hs/1/96]</note>
	</date>
	<date resp="#author-Creyssent" cert="false" evidence="internal" when="1771-12-24" n="date_alt1"/>
	[...] 
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div xml:id="c-6-1-2">
						<head>Alternative calendars</head>
						<div xml:id="c-1-2-1">
							<head>Phenomenon: Unclear conversion of a Roman letter date</head>
							<p n="32">Implementation:</p>
							<figure>
								<head>Example 5: Giovanni Bianchi to Albrecht von Haller, Rimini, 23
									June 1759 Brief (Editions- und Forschungsplattform hallerNet,
										<ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_00570">https://hallernet.org/letter_00570</ref>).</head>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] <date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="external" cert="false" when="1759-06-23">
		<note type="evidence">Nach
			<bibl>Grotefend</bibl>.</note>
	</date>
	<note type="alternativeDate">
		<date calendar="roman">9.Cal.Quint.</date>
		<date when="1759-04-23">
			<note>Mit "Quint" könnte auch Mai gemeint sein, das
			ergäbe den 23.4. als Briefdatum.</note>
		</date>
	</note> [...]
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="33">Explication: The editor identifies two ways to interpret the date. He
								lends more credibility to the date calculated after Grotefend and
								enters the corresponding date as the main metadata but he also
								describes the alternative possibility.</p>
							<p n="34">Alternative implementation (several <gi>date</gi> elements in
									<gi>correspAction</gi>):</p>
							<figure>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref"> [...] <date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="external" cert="false" when="1759-06-23" n="date_pref">
		<note type="evidence">Nach <bibl>Grotefend</bibl>. Mit
			"Quint" könnte auch Mai gemeint sein, das ergäbe den
			23.4. als Briefdatum.</note>
	</date>
	<date resp="#editor-XY" evidence="external" cert="false" when="1759-04-23" n="date_alt1">
		<note type="evidence">Wenn mit "Quint" Mai gemeint sein
			soll, ergibt sich der 23.4. als Briefdatum.</note>
	</date>
	<date calendar="roman" n="date_alt2">9.Cal.Quint.</date>
	[...] 
</correspAction>
</egXML>
							</figure>
							<p n="35">For all examples shown here, both variants allow processing routines
								to select the preferred date and, depending on the application, e.g.
								to be included in a register or search index or to be provided via
								an interface. The nested approach seems better suited towards
								interoperability as the prioritised date is reliably defined with a
								simple XPath expression
									(<hi>//correspAction[<att>type</att>="sent|received"]/date</hi>).</p>
							<p n="36">It should be noted that this article covers the selection of a date
								element but not yet the intended processing of the date attributes
								from the <hi>datable</hi>- and <hi>duration</hi> classes such as
									<att>notBefore</att>, <att>notAfter</att>, <att>from</att>,
									<att>to</att>, or <att>dur</att> (with the respective
									<hi>iso-</hi>, <hi>w3c-</hi> und <hi>custom</hi>-variants), as
								they are often used to encode time spans and dates that cannot be
								defined precisely.<note n="9" xml:id="fn9">Cf. e.g. section 5.1
									("Dates") of the encoding guidelines of the edition <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/?en">Letters
										and Texts. Intellectual Berlin around 1800</ref>, <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf#page=53">https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf</ref>.</note>
								The interpretation and processing of such attribute values ​​by
								processing routines lies beyond the scope of this text.<note n="10" xml:id="fn10">Some of the challenges regarding the processing of
									date attributes may be avoided by encouraging the use of
									specific dates with <att>precision</att>="medium". See <ref target="https://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/supp-historigdate.html">https://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/supp-historigdate.html</ref>
									and <ref target="https://lsv.uky.edu/scripts/wa.exe?A2=MARKUP;7412fa2e.1901">https://lsv.uky.edu/scripts/wa.exe?A2=MARKUP;7412fa2e.1901</ref>
									for recommendations of the EpiDoc community. Another interesting
									point of vantage is the Extended Date/Time Format (EDTF), cf.
										<ref target="https://www.loc.gov/standards/datetime/edtf.html">https://www.loc.gov/standards/datetime/edtf.html</ref>.</note></p>
						</div>
					</div>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="c-6-2">
					<head>Locations</head>
					<div xml:id="c-6-2-1">
						<head>Phenomenon: The location is missing in the original and is assigned by
							the editor</head>
						<p n="37">Implementation:</p>
						<figure>
							<head>Example 6: Heinrich Eberhard Balck to Albrecht von Haller,
								Hanover, January 1746 (Editions- und Forschungsplattform hallerNet,
									<ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_00178">https://hallernet.org/letter_00178</ref>).</head>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] <placeName key="#place_00603" resp="#editor-XY" cert="true" evidence="conjecture">Hannover
			<note>Ohne Ortsangabe im Original.</note>
	</placeName> [...] </correspAction>
</egXML>
						</figure>
						<p n="38">Explication: While no place of dispatch is given in the original, the
							editor specifies Hanover. By specifying "conjecture" in
								<att>evidence</att>, the editorial action is made transparent. The
							degree of certainty provided by the use of <att>cert</att> is given here
							according to the default value and therefore strictly speaking not
							necessary.</p>
						<p n="39">Alternative implementation:</p>
						<figure>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref #place_00603"> […]
		<placeName key="#place_00603" resp="#editor-XY" evidence="conjecture">Hannover</placeName>
	<placeName evidence="internal"/> […] </correspAction>
</egXML>
						</figure>
						<p n="40">This example shows two differing reference schemes used in
								<att>select</att> to define which date and which location should be
							considered for further processing (technical/analytical). This could be
							remediated relatively easily by adding
								<hi><att>ana</att>|<att>n</att>="place_pref"</hi> to the preferred
								<gi>placeName</gi> element (or perhaps better yet by the
							introduction of an <att>selection</att> to the TEI Guidelines as a
							counterpart for <att>select</att>) but all of this falls back beyond the
							less ambiguous hierarchical approach.</p>
					</div>
					<div xml:id="c-6-2-2">
						<head>Phenomenon: The location is unclear and is assigned by the editor</head>
						<p n="41">Implementation:</p>
						<figure>
							<head>Example 6: Natale Giuseppe Pallucci to Albrecht von Haller,
								Vienna, 2nd June 1763 (Editions- und Forschungsplattform hallerNet,
									<ref target="https://hallernet.org/letter_13032">https://hallernet.org/letter_13032</ref>).</head>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent"> [...] <placeName key="#place_01130" source="#letter_13916" evidence="conjecture" resp="#editor-XY">Wien <note>Wien nach <rs key="#letter_13916">AvH.s Brief an S. Tissot [K] vom
				16.6.1763</rs></note>
	</placeName>
</correspAction>
</egXML>
						</figure>
						<p n="42">Explication: While no place of dispatch is given in the original, the
							editor specifies Vienna. The fact that this conjecture is based on
							another letter becomes apparent in <att>source</att> and its specifics
							are explained in a note element. Notwithstanding the omission of
								<att>cert</att>, this information is certain (default value
							"true").</p>
						<p n="43">Alternative implementation:</p>
						<figure>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="sent" select="#date_pref #place_01130"> […]
		<placeName key="#place_01130" source="#letter_13916" resp="#editor-XY" evidence="conjecture">Wien <note>Wien nach
				<rs key="#letter_13916">AvH.s Brief an S. Tissot [K]
				vom 16.6.1763</rs></note>
	</placeName>
	<placeName evidence="internal"/> […] </correspAction>
</egXML>
						</figure>
					</div>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="c-6-3">
					<head>Persons</head>
					<div xml:id="c-6-3-1">
						<head>Phenomenon: Sender and/or recipient are uncertain</head>
						<p n="44">The two strategies discussed and shown above are equally applicable to
							uncertain senders and recipients. Again, a <gi>correspAction</gi> might
							contain the most likely senders and recipients in <gi>persName</gi>
							elements for the sent and received actions and record more precise
							information in a note.</p>
						<figure>
							<head>Example 6: Theodor Fontane to Unknown (Anna von Hochenburger?), 23
								January 1890 Vienna, 2nd June 1763 (Berbig, Roland. 2010. Theodor
								Fontane Chronik, p. 3078).</head>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="received"> […] <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118534262" resp="#editor-XY">Fontane, Theodor</persName> […] </correspAction>
<correspAction type="received"> […] <persName ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023503034" resp="#editor-XY" evidence="external" cert="medium">Hochenburger, Anna von
			<note>Vgl. <bibl>Berbig, Theodor Fontane. Chronik, S.
				3078</bibl>.</note>
	</persName> […] </correspAction></egXML>
						</figure>
						<p n="45">Alternatively, all possible options could be encoded in <gi>persName</gi>
							elements directly within <gi>correspAction</gi> and prioritised using
								<att>select</att> on <gi>correspAction</gi> (using pointers such as
								<hi>#sender_pref</hi> or <hi>#recipient_pref</hi>).</p>
						<figure>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correspAction type="received" select="#recipient_pref"> […]
		<persName n="recipient_pref" ref="http://d-nb.info/gnd/1023503034" resp="#editor-XY" evidence="conjecture" cert="medium">Hochenburger, Anna
		von</persName>
	<persName n="pers_alt1">unknown</persName> […] </correspAction>
</egXML>
						</figure>
					</div>
				</div>
			</div>
			<!-- hier weiter -->
			<div type="bibliography">
				<head>Bibliography</head>
				<listBibl>
					<bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/MFJ24FJR/"> Baillot, Anne, et al. 2013ff. Edition-specific TEI encoding guidelines for
						the digital edition "Letters and texts. Intellectual Berlin around 1800"
						["Briefe und Texte aus dem intellektuellen Berlin um 1800"] <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf">https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf</ref>
						(last accessed: 7 August 2020).</bibl>
					<bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/B9FKUDZJ/"> Berbig, Roland. 2010. Theodor Fontane Chronik. Berlin/New York.</bibl>
					<bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/3FKUXPAN/">Kuczera, Andreas, Wübbena, Thorsten, and Thomas Kollatz (eds.). 2019. Die
						Modellierung des Zweifels — Schlüsselideen und -konzepte zur graphbasierten
						Modellierung von Unsicherheiten. Wolfenbüttel. (Zeitschrift für digitale
						Geisteswissenschaften / Sonderbände, 4). DOI: 10.17175/sb004.</bibl>
					<bibl sameAs="https://www.zotero.org/groups/2248469/encoding_correspondence/items/itemKey/A3F94BIQ">TEI Consortium, eds. TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
						Interchange. Version 3.6.0. Last updated on 16th July 2019. TEI Consortium.
							<ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html">https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html</ref> (last
						accessed: 7 August 2020).</bibl>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>